<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The manifest of the most illustrious, and soveraigne prince, Charles Lodovvick, Count Palatine of the Rhine, Prince Electour of the sacred Empire: Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c. Concerning the right of his succession both in the princedome, lands, and estates of the Palatinate: as also in the dignity, voice, session, and function of the electorship-Palatine thereunto annexed. Translated, anno. M.DC.XXXVII.</title>
            <title>Manifestum sive deductio. English</title>
            <author>Karl Ludwig, Elector Palatine, 1617-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843460</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1093:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The manifest of the most illustrious, and soveraigne prince, Charles Lodovvick, Count Palatine of the Rhine, Prince Electour of the sacred Empire: Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c. Concerning the right of his succession both in the princedome, lands, and estates of the Palatinate: as also in the dignity, voice, session, and function of the electorship-Palatine thereunto annexed. Translated, anno. M.DC.XXXVII.</title>
                  <title>Manifestum sive deductio. English</title>
                  <author>Karl Ludwig, Elector Palatine, 1617-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[nne] G[riffin] for I[oyce] N[orton] and R[ichard] W[hitaker] And are to be sold at the signe of the Kings Armes in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXXVII. [1637]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Manifestum sive deductio.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publishers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [fleuron]⁴ (only third leaf signed) A-T⁴+.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>STC reports copies with additional text with heading "An advertisement to the reader", collating chi¹ ("A2") B-H⁴ I¹, referring to the present manifesto. G2 has separate title page, "The protestation [..?]. London, 1637" (formerly STC 5049), followed by a different (earlier?) version of "A protestation of the most high and mighty prince Charles Lodowicke".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Palatinate (Germany) --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Palatinate (Germany) --  History --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:1"/>
            <p>THE MANIFEST OF The Moſt Illuſtrious, and Soveraigne Prince, Charles Lodowick, Count Palatine of the Rhine, Prince Electour of the Sacred Empire: Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Right of His <hi>Succeſsion Both in the</hi> Princedome, Lands, <hi>and</hi> Eſtates of the PALATINATE: As alſo in the Dignity, Voice, Seſſion and Function of the ELECTORSHIP-PALATINE thereunto annexed.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated, <hi>Anno.</hi> M.DC.XXXVII.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A.G.</hi> for <hi>I.N.</hi> and <hi>R.W.</hi> And are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Kings Armes in <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> M.DC.XXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He State of Empires, Kingdoms, and all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, is beſt knowne, by thoſe Lawes, Orders, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, and Conſtitutions, which, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent, are, for the time being eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed amongſt them: for State is from ſtanding; and that preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein a thing ſtandeth, is the State thereof. What hath been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or may bee hereafter, doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belong to their Story, than their State. By this Line we may meaſure
<pb facs="tcp:8197:3"/>the Germane Empire; at it hath long ſtood, and yet standeth, though like an old houſe nodding to the ground. J will not deſcribe the whole frame ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but onely ſuch parts as may give light to the enſuing diſcourſe. Looke wee therefore backe to former times, and we ſhall finde, that <hi>Germany,</hi> like a vaſt body, was cut and mangled into divers Nations, Formes and Governments, till the Raigne of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great about <hi>800</hi> and odd yeeres agoe. Jn His dayes, the great Roman Empire ſplit into two; whereof the Weſterne part fell to His ſhare, which Hee after ſubdivided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong His ſons. <hi>Charles</hi> had <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Lodowick</hi> had <hi>France, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> had <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:3"/>
            <p>But <hi>Germany,</hi> is the greateſt, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away the Imperiall Title from the rest; which cauſed great diſſentions, not onely betwixt the three pretending Nations, but alſo among the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> after <hi>Charlemaines</hi> Line was out. At laſt <hi>Hugh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet</hi> ſetting up a new Race in <hi>France,</hi> to ſecure His owne poſterity, was willing to let fall the ſtrife for the Title, and yeelded it to <hi>Germany:</hi> But <hi>Italy</hi> toſſed with the furies and ambitions of the Popes, ever rebelled againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, and inward broyles fowlly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced. <hi>Germany;</hi> Till at length the Princes, tyred and conſumed with theſe evills, were forced to adviſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their owne preſervation, and the Empires. Then was produced this
<pb facs="tcp:8197:4"/>forme of State, which hath continued without change, many hundred yeeres. Firſt they made a Law, That the Emperor, from thence forwards, ſhould be choſen among themſelves, whereby all pretentions ſhould bee reſtrained. Next, they appointed the chooſers; whereof, according to thoſe times, three were Biſhops, <hi>Mentz, Tryers</hi> and <hi>Collen;</hi> and three Princes, the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine, Saxe,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg.</hi> Theſe ſixe doe onely, and properly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute that Colledge, which is called the Supreame Councell of the Emperour, and Foundation of the Empire. But becauſe their number was even, and in Elections it muſt be odd, the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was added to them, that in the Colledge might be a caſting voyce:
<pb facs="tcp:8197:4"/>for He hath onely Electorall Right at times of election, and is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver elſe admitted into the Dyets or Councels of the Colledge. This Colledge was then ordained with prepetuall elective power: Inſomuch that when any was choſen by the Chapters of Mentz, Tryer, or Collen to bee Biſhops, they were immediately likewiſe Electours; but becauſe they could not marry, and were alwaies choſen, there was no need to povide for their ſucceſsion. But the caſe was different of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours temporall: For they being great and Soveraigne Princes, before they were Electours, had no meaning to make there Eſtate worſe by that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: And therefore it was enacted
<pb facs="tcp:8197:5"/>as an irrevocable Law, that their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Dignities, and Temporall Princedomes ſhould goe together, and bee entayled upon their eldeſt Sonnes and Heire-males deſcending from them, by the Fathers ſide for ever.</p>
            <p>For they held in neceſſary to cleare the Succeſsion in thoſe Houſes, which had perpetuall Right to chooſe the Emperour, well fore-ſeeing, that it might bee no leſſe pernitious to the whole body, to diſpute who ſhould be Electour, than it was before, who ſhould be Emperour: whereas now the whole Empire might certainely know, where the Dignity would deſcend, and ſo be alwaies at reſt; from whence it appeareth, that on the certainety of the Colledge, the Jafety of the Empire
<pb facs="tcp:8197:5"/>dependeth. Now this Right of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is ſo rooted in theſe Electorall Fami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lies, and in every one of their Male off-ſpring, that it cannot bee plucked up, nor alienated, nor forfeited, nor transferred by any reſignation, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquencie; but onely by failing and extinction of blood; in which ſole caſe, both the Dignity and Inheritance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertes unto the Empire, as a Fee thereof. The ſumme of all, is, that by this Policie and Conſtitution of the Empire, which hath bin confirmed by ſuch continuance of time, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is Elective, and the Electours Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsive; and in the mutuall oathes, which paſſe betwixt them, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is bound deeper to them, and by them to the Empire, to preſerve them
<pb facs="tcp:8197:6"/>all in their immunities, than they to him, who onely ſweare homage and fealty, not as His, but as vaſſals of the Empire. In which relation, if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any, or Electour, or of an Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Houſe ſhall commit the higheſt crime, though as great as Treaſon, yet they cannot bee puniſhed, much leſſe depoſed by any power of the Emperour, who is not the Lord of their Fee, but by a lawfull tryall before the Electorall Colledge and eſtates of the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, of which onely they doe depend. As vaſſals of the Empire, they may be tryed for their offence, and puniſhed in their owne perſons: but as Princes and Soveraignes in their eſtates, they cannot be tainted in blood, nor by their crime prejudice the ſucceſsion of
<pb facs="tcp:8197:6"/>their Heires; which is the difference betwixt the Regally of theſe Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Tenures, and thoſe of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for their treaſon doth taint the blood, and diſableth the Sonne to ſucceed the Father, becauſe the Sonne ſucceeds in the Fathers Right; which the Father having forfeited, the Sonne hath nothing to ſucceed; but heere the Sonne ſucceedeth not in the Right of his Father, but of his owne; by reaſon of that firſt and Originall Contract made with his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours, wherein Hee was inveſted and comprehended, as well as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and cannot be excluded from his owne Right, but by his owne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Which ſeemeth to bee a moſt juſt, and naturall ſanction, That
<pb facs="tcp:8197:7"/>if every owne will looke to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, the Law will looke to his Right. And this may ſuffice for a ſmall Jntroduction to the worke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:7"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:8"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>CHARLES LODOWIKE</hi> By the Grace of God, Count Palatine of the Rhine: Archidapifer, and Prince Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of the Sacred Empire, Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To his Imperiall Maieſty.</salute>
               <salute>To all Kings, Potentates, Electors, Princes, and Eſtates; within the Empire and whole Chriſtendome.</salute>
               <salute>Addreſſeth This his enſuing Manifeſt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:8"/>
            <head>The Manifeſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene the conſtant cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſundry Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world, from the beginning thereof, to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age; that in all hereditary kingdoms and principalities, the ſucceſſion ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend upon the eldeſt Sonne, or the next males in blood to the deceaſed, without let or contradiction.</p>
            <p>And as this Right of Birth and preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of nature is large and univerſall; ſo in eſpeciall manner it hath beene confirmed, and obſerved moſt exactly in the Electorall
<pb facs="tcp:8197:9"/>houſes of the Germane Empire: inſomuch that many hundred yeeres agoe, when it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good to the preceding Emperors, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Eſtates of the Empire, to found and erect the Colledge of Electors, as well for the ſetling of a good order, as for preventing of all diviſions. They decreed by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent, and ripe deliberation, that the three Electorall houſes of the Palatinate, Saxony and Brandenburgh ſhould from thence forwards, and for ever after, have their certaine and unqueſtionable ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in their Electorall Office; and Eſtates and Regalities thereunto annexed. Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning moreover, that whenſoever any of the ſaid Electors ſhould depart this world, then his firſt borne Sonne and the male iſſue, or in default thereof, the next of that<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Agnation</hi> is that Line in blood, which comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the Couſins or male-deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents on the Fathers ſide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire are only capable to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Houſes.</note> 
               <hi>Agnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> ſhould be received, and acknowledged by all the States of the Empire, for true and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Electours. Or if perchance they were under yeeres, that then they ſhould be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Succeſſors deſigned, and in due time inveſted by the Emperours raigning in the right of their succeſsions. Which wiſe and
<pb facs="tcp:8197:9"/>wholeſome Ordination, whereby the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire had ſo long time been peaceably gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, was againe in the yeere 1356 at the intervention of all the Electors, Princes and Eſtates, ratified and eſtabliſhed for a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Law of the Empire by the <hi>Golden</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">So called from Bulla; the ſtampe or ſeale of gold, which was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended to this imperiall Charter here mentioned; wherein was contained all the laws, forms and orders, of the Empire; both for choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour as Head, and preſerving the Eſtates as Members in their ſeverall liberties, rites and lignities.</note> 
               <hi>Bull of Charles</hi> IV. <hi>then Emperour.</hi> In ſuch ſort, that all Conſtitutions of the Empire, and<note n="c" place="margin">Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours were agreed of the perſon, before they declare Him Emperour, they required an oath of Him, to maintaine the Lawes of the Empire, and preſerve them, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates thereof, in their ſeverall Rights and Immunities. And this is called the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Capitulation.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Capitulations</hi> of the Emperour together with the mutuall bonds and unions betwixt Electors, which have ſince that time beene made and contracted, were laid and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon this fundamentall Sanction; and whatſoever hath been contriued to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice thereof, held for illegall, and of no validity. The word of the Golden Bull, whereby the right of Birth and Succeſſion is inviolably preſerved in the Electorall Houſes, follow in this forme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:10"/>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note>That hereafter, no diſpute nor diſſention ariſe betweene the Sons of the ſaid Electours, and Princes temporall, and that the publike good and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſuffer no ſtop nor detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We, deſirous to remove all ſuch impediments, Doe by this preſent Act, never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, declare, will, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, by Our Imperiall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; That when any of the ſaid Electours ſhall deceaſe, his Right, Vote, and power Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ſhall deſcend to his eldeſt Sonne, being ſecular and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in lawfull marriage; and by his deceaſe to his eldeſt Son without any oppoſition. And in caſe the eldeſt Sonne ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:8197:10"/>depart without lawfull heires, being ſecular; then the Right, Vote, and power Elective ſhall be transferred by vertue of this Act to his next brother by the fathers ſide, lawfull and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and ſo ſucceſsively unto his eldeſt Son. Furthermore, this Succeſsion in the eldeſt Sons and lawfull heires of Electors, and Princes, concerning their Right, Vote, and power Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, ſhall from hence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be for ever preciſely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved with this Declaration; That if perchance and Electour his firſt borne Son, or his next eldeſt brother, of the firſt borne Son, ſhall have the Tuition and Adminiſtration, till He accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh
<pb facs="tcp:8197:11"/>his Maiority, which in an Electour ſhall be eighteene yeeres Compleate, at the end whereof, the Right, Vote, and Elective power, with all the appurtenances, ſhall devolve upon him, which together with the Electorall Office, ſhall bee reſigned to him by the ſaid Tutour and Adminiſtratour.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Since therefore by the death of the moſt Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> V. Count Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of the Rhine, and Duke of Bavaria, and afterwards choſen King of Bohemia, Our moſt Honoured Lord and Father of happy memory, the office of <hi>High</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">For more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Coronation, the foure tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Electors doe the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſervice for that Day: King of Bohemia giveth him Drinke, as Cupbearer: Electour Palatine ſetteth on the firſt Diſh, as Sewer, which is called <hi>Truckceſſe:</hi> The Electour Saxony carrieth the Sword, as Marſhall: and Electour Brandenburg, beareth the Key, as Chamberlaine.</note> Truck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and Electourſhip of the Empire, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the Rights, Suffrage, Dignities, Regalities, Lands, People and Subjects
<pb facs="tcp:8197:11"/>thereon depending, are fallen unto Vs, and that by vertue of Our proper and acquired Birth-right of the Contract and providence of our Anceſtours: of all Feodall lawes: of the firſt <hi>&amp;</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">So called from Simul together: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when a Prince or Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour is inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the Emperour, it gathereth and includeth all the reſt of his blood and Agnation, and entitleth them to the ſame Right of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion with himſelfe; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by every one ſuccedeth in his owne Right, and can neither foreſee more than he hath, nor be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced by the forfeiture of another.</note> 
               <hi>Simultaneous Inveſtiture:</hi> of the Golden Bull: of Imperiall Charters: of fundamentall Lawes: of<note n="f" place="margin">By theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, All thoſe in every Electorall Houſe, who appertaine to the male blood or Agnation, are bound to obſerve the foreſaid order in their ſeverall ſucceſſions; which is eſtabliſhed by the ancient and publike Conſtitutions of the Empire: namely, which deſcendeth upon the Eldeſt Sonne and ſo forward to the next male Couſin in blood by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide.</note> 
               <hi>Covenants made</hi> in our Electorall Houſe: and of the Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of many foregoing Emperours, they are inſeparably intailed upon us. And ſince Our dearely beloved Vnckle by Our Fathers ſide, the Duke of Simmern hath in conformity to the Golden Bull reſigned as well the Tuition of Our Perſon, as Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Our Eſtates at the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed: We having, as it became us, waited the time, and now by the grace of God, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained our full age, doe thinke Our ſelves bound in honour and conſcience, to take upon Vs the Succeſſion of Our Electorall Dignity, and all things thereunto belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:12"/>as that whereunto God, Nature, and Our Right hath called Vs. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe We doe now preſent our ſelves both to your Imperiall Majeſty, (of whom We have in due forme demanded Our Inveſtiture) as alſo to have all Kings, Electours, Princes, and Eſtates, in that Electorall quality, which belongeth to our Birth and Succeſſion, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, that yee will not onely, receive and acknowledge Vs therein, but alſo aſſiſt and maintaine Vs in Our illitigable Right.</p>
            <p>Here at our entrance, Wee can eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that the Ban againſt Our moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Lord and Father, the execution of the ſame, together with the tranſlation of Our Electourſhip (which is ſtill detayned by force) may be caſt into Our way by partiall and cold affected people: but We intreate them all to ſpare their judgements, and looke a little backwards upon the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and juſt Defences, which have beene made both in publike writings, and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, there they ſhall finde the complaints of the temporall Electours againſt thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt proceedings, and the nullities of the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:12"/>ſame, to be proved incurable. And if need-full it were to enlarge thoſe deductions, which are already publiſhed to the world; We are to know, that our ſaid Lord and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not long before his death cauſed his juſt Apologie to bee drawne in writing againſt thoſe violent proceedings, with a purpoſe to have put it out, but that He feared, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion might have beene taken from thence to have hindred ſome treaties and media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions then a foote, ſince it hath beene ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by his untimely death, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had it ſeene the light, would queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe have imprinted better opinions in the minds of thoſe, who have beene choked with blinde and ſiniſter informations. For the preſent We referre the clearing of thoſe matters to the publike bookes afore mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and referre expreſſely to our ſelves the defence and vindication of Our moſt deare Lord and Fathers honour, by all lawfull waies, againſt falſe and calumnious impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, hoping that no living ſoule can with reaſon blame this duty in a Chriſtian and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient ſonne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:13"/>
            <p>But in this paſſage, We cannot conceale the inwardneſſe of Our griefe, to ſee the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of Our Electorall Rights not onely uſurped by force of armes, but juſtified and confirmed by the late Treaty of peace made at Prague the 30 <hi>of May</hi> laſt, under this pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted pretext, as if forſooth the whole world, and in particular the Electorall Colledge aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in the yeare 1627 had found and charged Our moſt deare Lord and Father, as chiefe Authour of all the broyles, happened firſt in Bohemia, and afterwards throughout the Empire: whereas the contrary was ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly repreſented, and avouched to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour by the whole Electorall Colledge and Diete at Ratisbone in the yeare 1623 <hi>the</hi> 30 <hi>of Ianuary,</hi> as appeareth by their joynt relation, as followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <p>That the Palatine was a yong Prince, and not being able to Counſell Himſelfe, was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by others. That He was not the Authour of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb facs="tcp:8197:13"/>in Bohemia, and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who had no leſſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded His Imperiall Maieſty, had beene pardoned. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they all beſought His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty to overcome Himſelfe by his owne magnanimity, and to turne His rigour into gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereby the Palatine upon due deprecation might bee admitted to grace, and the Empire be refreſhed and ſetled in peace. Otherwiſe, if the waies of extremity were ſtill continued, nothing could be looked for but effuſion of blood, vaſtation of the Empire with new and fearefull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtions.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This was at that time the opinion of the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:14"/>ſaid Electours, which notwithſtanding they ſtrangely changed afterwards in the Diete at <hi>Mulhauſen,</hi> though they had leſſe cauſe than before.</p>
            <p>Now it is Manifeſt enough, and might eaſily bee further cleared, with what zeale, and ſincerity Our moſt honoured Lord and Father laboured to quench that fire, which others had kindled, and to obtaine the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and reconciliation of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour together with his owne reſtitution; The many Treaties, offers, ſubmiſſions, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions, cautions made by Our moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lord and Father, together with the frequent Ambaſſages, Interceſſions, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances of divers Kings, Potentates, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, Princes, and Eſtates in this behalfe, are ſo many witneſſes of His paines and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity.</p>
            <p>To paſſe over the friendly diligences, which Our moſt honoured Lord and Father uſed to ſtill and appeaſe the firſt ruptures of Bohemia, as alſo what Hee propounded to the Electour of Saxony, and Landgrave of Darmſtatt after the battaile of Prague tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:8197:14"/>His own reconciliation. We will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly produce the teſtimony of ſome <hi>Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> in this place, which were ſent to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour by the Kings and Allyes, &amp; at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Our moſt honoured Lord and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The firſt was <hi>Anno</hi> 1621. when the Lords of Rantzow and Winterſheim were diſpatched to Vienna from the King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, reiterated againe <hi>Anno</hi> 1622. by the Lord Bogwiſch of Haſlow, ſeconded with the Letters and interceſſion of the Electour of Saxony. The ſecond ſort are thoſe Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſages which were imployed to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour by the late King of Great Britaine Our Grandfather of bleſſed memory; namely by the Earle of Carlile 1619. by Sir <hi>Henry Wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> 1620. by Sir <hi>Edward Conway</hi> 1621. and Sir <hi>Richard Weſton</hi> in the ſame yeere, by the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> 1621. by the ſaid Sir <hi>Richard Weſton</hi> at Bruxells, beſides all thoſe Treaties in Spain and elſewhere, negotiated by His o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ambaſſadors. The third ſort are part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Letters ſent to the Emperour by the ſaid King of Great Britaine, before the tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:8197:15"/>of Our Electorall Dignity, under the date of 12. <hi>November,</hi> 1621. Wherein divers Conditions were propounded to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Houſe of Auſtria, and partly the conference at Colmar in <hi>Iuly</hi> 1627 with the Dukes of Lorraine and Wirttenberg; who were admitted as Interpoſers by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour himſelfe, together with our Offers, and Declarations, which were there made upon the foure Articles, propounded in the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors name by the Prince of Eggenberg. The fourth ſort are thoſe two ſolemne Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which the King of Great Britaine our moſt Royall Vncle, ſent by Sir <hi>Robert An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruther</hi> to the Emperour, and Electors aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Ratisbone</hi> 1630. and to Vienna to the Emperour <hi>apart</hi> 1631. And laſtly We referre our ſelves to thoſe diverſe writings and letters, which Our moſt honoured Lord and Father ſent abroad to Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: but eſpecially to thoſe two, which He wrote with his owne hand unto the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. By all which (though barely recounted as paſſing by) it plainely appeareth, that Our moſt honoured Lord and Father omitted
<pb facs="tcp:8197:15"/>no poſſible meanes to ſeeke and ſue for his reconcilement, preferring alwaies the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like peace before His private intereſt, and what He could not doe by himſelfe or his Miniſters, by reaſon of the Ban againſt Him, He laboured to effect by the mediation of great Kings and Princes His Allyes, ever willing to ſubmit himſelfe to reaſon; which doth not onely diſcharge Him of thoſe wrongfull imputations, as though He by his practiſes, ſtubborneneſſe and rejection of all equitable meanes had beene the chiefe cauſe of theſe miſerable warres and ruines in the Empire, but alſo diſcover, that the fault is to be truely imputed to them, who diſdainefully waving theſe many offers, inſtances, and interceſsions of peace, have driven all things to extremities, to glut the covetouſneſſe and ambitions of their hearts.</p>
            <p>But who will looke into the letters of his Imperiall Majeſty, written with his owne hand the 14 &amp; 15. of October 1621. to Don <hi>Balthazar</hi> of Zuniga one of the Councellers and Grandees of Spaine, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:8197:16"/>there find other reaſons, &amp; indeed the true cauſes, which moved His Majeſty to thinke it moſt neceſſary then, to transferre our Electorall Dignity upon the Duke of Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria without delay. For after many conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations alledgd, which made him reſolve never to reſtore Our ſaid Lord and Father, He thus writeth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Letters of the Emperour for tranſlation of the Electour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Palatine to the Duke of Bavaria.</note>Since we have concluded with our ſelves, even before God gave us this great victory, That the Palatine once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed could no more be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored without manifeſt danger of the Catholicke party, and all our houſe; and conſidering that the Duke of Bavaria is a Zealous Defender of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke cauſe, and that his Countrey is a Bulwarke for ours againſt the Dutch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Wee have of our owne
<pb facs="tcp:8197:16"/>proper motion, but inſpired, no doubt, from God, given the Palatine Electorſhip unto him, as to a Prince endowed with great riches, and full of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to beare ſo high a Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And foraſmuch as his help and ſervices have ſtood us much in ſtead, and may be ſtill of great uſe unto us, for reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering Our Kingdomes and Eſtates; The time it ſelfe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to require it more, than he, that we haſten the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of our promiſe, in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Electourſhip upon him, whereby wee ſhall alſo eaſe our ſelves of much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and cut off all hope from
<pb facs="tcp:8197:17"/>the Palatine and His friends, who with too much importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity preſſe his reſtitution. And becauſe this worke needeth the aſsiſtance of the King of Spaine, we have thought by your meanes earneſtly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him, not to neglect this fit occaſion, to advance the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Our Houſe, and the cauſe of Religion, to both which He is well inclined. For he cannot be ignorant, that in this opinion Our Anceſtours were confirmed, that the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and pillars of Our Houſe were laid and grounded in Germany, which ought with ſo much the more care be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb facs="tcp:8197:17"/>againſt Our enemies, becauſe if the foundations be ſhaken, the Fabricke cannot long ſubſiſt: Now among all Adverſaries againſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Our Houſe, none hath beene more oppoſite, within the bounds of Germany, than the Count Palatins, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the time of <hi>Maximil.</hi> I. <hi>Charles</hi> V. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> I. and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph</hi> II. This being certaine, that the rebellion of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands againſt His grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Philip</hi> II. was fomented from the Palatinate, and that He will never bee able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to His obedience, unleſſe this Stocke bee firſt
<pb facs="tcp:8197:18"/>rooted out of the Empire.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In the poſtſcript of the ſaid Letter this motive was likewiſe added;</p>
            <q>
               <p>That if we had one Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like voyce more, than wee have, we ſhould alſo be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the Empire would remaine in the Catholike hands, and by conſequence in Our Houſe, to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof, the Duke of Bavaria would willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in requitall of this great benefit, having beene exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by an Emperour of Our Houſe to ſo High a Dignity.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In another Letter of the Emperours, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the King of Spaine, under the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>May</hi> 1622 are theſe words;</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:18"/>
            <q>
               <p>Since it may be preſumed that the Engliſh Ambaſſadour hath Commiſsion amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things to urge the reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Palatine now exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; We thought good to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you in confidence, that We have lately promiſed, for many reaſons, the Electorall Dignity and Prerogative fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into Our hands, unto the Duke of Bavaria, as to one, who during theſe publike troubles and confuſions hath well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of Vs, of the Empire, of Religion, and of Our houſe, and ſtill ceaſeth not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe infinite charges, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the danger of his life and
<pb facs="tcp:8197:19"/>Eſtates, inſomuch as having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready granted Him our letters Patents, nothing now remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but what dependeth on time and occaſion, namely to give Him inveſtiture, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce Him into the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Colledge, and ſo to put Him in full poſſeſsion.</p>
            </q>
            <p>If any man would know the foule and the fayre of this pretended promiſe, and tranſlation of the Electourſhip, how it was negotiated, contrived and agreed, by the ſuggeſtion of the Pope, and operation of certaine Monkes, as alſo how it was ſecretly carryed and concealed from the Colledge of Electours, who were afterwards aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> onely to approve the ſaid tranſlation, and to aſsiſt the ſolemne Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture with their preſence, we ſhall ſend the Reader to the Publike Acts, and originall
<pb facs="tcp:8197:19"/>letters, out of which theſe things following, are extracted: Firſt in the Emperours letter of his own hand to <hi>Don Balthazar de Zuniga</hi> bearing date 15 of <hi>October</hi> 1621. are theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Moreover I cannot for beare to acquaint you, that ſince wee have divers times both by word and writing promiſed the Duke of Bavaria (who hath ſo much obliged us) to transfer the Electourſhip Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine upon him: We know not by what meanes we can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw our promiſes without wounding our honour, and provoking Gods anger againſt us. </p>
            </q>
            <p>In another letter written with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous owne hand to <hi>Hiacynthus</hi> a <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin,</hi> bearing date 15 <hi>October</hi> 1621.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:20"/>
            <q>
               <p>Although wee doubt not, but you will handle the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe committed to your charg with that wiſedome, God hath given you, yet for the truſt we have put in you, wee will not for beare to give you this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe; That ye ſhould not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Court of Spaine, that the Duke of Bavaria hath already the Inveſtiture in his hands, for we feare, that if they ſhould know ſo much, it would infallibly breed rather harme than good, but ye ſhall rather labour to rectifie thoſe errours, which are currant there, and diſpoſe them, not onely to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with our opinions, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8197:20"/>to aſsiſt us in our deſignes, that we may perfect this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed worke ſo neceſſary for the preſervation of our holy faith, and by conſequent, of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. For yee know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that if the King of Spayne ſhould abandon us, we were not able of our ſelves to make our promiſe good to the Duke of Bavaria.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In the Emperours Reſolution given in writing to the Popes Nuncio <hi>Fabritio Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſpo</hi> at <hi>Vienna,</hi> in <hi>February</hi> 1622 are theſe words:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reſolution of the Emperour about the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</note>His Imperiall Maieſty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving well conſidered, the preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant reaſons which moved his
<pb facs="tcp:8197:21"/>Holineſſe to perſwade him, to transferre upon the Duke of Bavaria the Electorall Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Titles, Honours taken from the Palatine proforibed, doth firſt of all duely thanke his Holineſſe, for ſhewing by ſo grave an Ambaſſage his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care, to increaſe the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion, and relieve the miſerable eſtate of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and that his Holineſſe might ſee the providence and care of his Maieſty concurring with him, in the ſame ayme and ends, Hee hath already begun that Tranſlation, which his Holineſſe deſired, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured the Duke of Bavaria
<pb facs="tcp:8197:21"/>thereof by his Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Count <hi>d'Ognate</hi> Spaniſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour at <hi>Vienna,</hi> cauſed a memoriall to bee preſented to the Pope by his brother Ambaſſadour then at Rome beginning thus:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hiacinthus</hi> the Capuchin was ſent by your Holineſſe to the Emperour to exhort Him, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to continue the warre againſt the Hereticks, Enemies of our Mother Church, and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to your Holineſſe; partly to diſpoſe him, to tranſlate the Electorall dignity upon the Duke of Bavaria, who both for his Religion, and his aſsiſtance in the warre againſt the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb facs="tcp:8197:22"/>hath well deſerved of the Emperour, ſo as the deſire of your Holineſſe is, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine ſhould be ſtripped of his Dignity and puniſhed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his deſert &amp; rebellion.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Cardinall <hi>Ludoviſius</hi> wrote from Rome the 16 of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1621. to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Patras</hi> Popes Nuncio at Bruxels, to this purpoſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Letters of the Cardinall Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doviſius about the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Yee ſhall uſe all poſsible meanes to diſwade the Infanta her Highneſſe from agreeing to a ſuſpenſion of Armes. And concerning the Perſon of the Palatine, my adviſe is, that ſince Hee is once deprived of his Countrey, Hee ought to
<pb facs="tcp:8197:22"/>take it for a ſpeciall grace if He may have leave to ſubmit himſelfe to the Emperour, but notwithſtanding any ſubmiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nothing ought to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his children, unleſſe they be brought up in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion. For it were a great errour to ſuffer the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate in the hands of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, which is ſo neare to the Low Countries. Therefore it behooveth you to be watchfull there, as well as the Nuntio is in Spayne, who hath order to imprint this point well in the Kings minde: The Pope will alſo doe his beſt to perſwade the Emperour, and the King of
<pb facs="tcp:8197:23"/>Spayne, that the Palatinate bee ſhared among the Catholicks, whereunto you ſhall doe very well to diſpoſe the Infanta.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Caraffa the Popes Nuntio at Vienna wrote to the forenamed Arch-Biſhop of Patras the 20 <hi>of October</hi> 1621 to Bruxels in this manner,<note place="margin">Letters of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raffa the Popes Nuntio about the Tranſlation.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>There is no doubt to bee made of the Emperours inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to transferre the Electour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Palatine upon the Duke of Bavaria: The only ſtop pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Spanyard, which I ſhould not have beene bold to ſay, had not the Prince of Eggenberg aſſured me, that the Emperour had finiſhed the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:23"/>buſineſſe long agoe but for the wilfulneſſe of the Spaniards, who for want of other evaſion cover their croſſeneſſe under the pretext of the Electour of Sax.: But to ſtop this ſtarting hole, the Arch-Duke Charles, is lately gone to the ſaid Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, <hi>though under another colour,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">The colour was to diſpoſe the ſaid Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of armes and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Ban, which at that time was promiſed by word of mouth to my Lord Digby.</note> from whom we ſhortly expect anſwer, which if it bee not a flat negative, but neutrall and indifferent, we will goe on, and urge the Emperour to diſpatch the worke, and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Count <hi>d'Ognate</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſay, that the King his Maſter will be content, if the Duke of Sax. be not contrary:
<pb facs="tcp:8197:24"/>Nevertheleſſe, becauſe we are iealous of the Counts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe, although the Duke of Sax. ſhould conſent, we have without noiſe and under hand ſent Fryar Hiacynthus into Spayne to blunt the indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the ſaid Count, and of Digby the Engliſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador deſigned to goe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to which end the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour hath written with his owne hand to the King of Spayne, to Don Balthazar, and the Nun Infanta, without the Knowledge of any. In ſumme, you ſee the ſtate of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and by diſcourſe of the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:8197:24"/>finde; that the Spaniard (on whom all dependeth) would not much oppoſe this tranſlation, if theſe three points were provided for. Firſt, that the Duke of Bavaria ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore upper Auſtria; That for defraying of his coſts Hee ſhould have the upper Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, which is more, than his due, and would content Him: And that the Nether Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, be left to them, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Duke of Bavaria ſhould renounce all the pretention, which He might have in right of the Electorall Dignity.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:25"/>
            <p>The ſaid Nuncio writing to Fryar <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acynthus</hi> the 16 <hi>of October</hi> 1627 ſaith as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth,</p>
            <q>
               <p>I beſought the Emperour to keepe the buſineſſe ſecret; who told me, He had already writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with his owne hand to the very cover, for the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy. And a little after, I drive on this buſineſſe with earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, albeit I ſomething doubt, whether it be neceſſary or no, ſeeing our friends are minded to doe that, which the Count of Zollerne cauſed to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by a Miniſter of the Emperours to the Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia a part; yee underſtand
<pb facs="tcp:8197:25"/>well, what I would ſay: I have given out, that ye are going in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Italy, and hitherto, they know no otherwiſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Moreover in another letter of the ſame Nuntio to the ſaid Capuchin of the 20 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1621 are theſe words:</p>
            <q>
               <p>The firſt Pretention of the Count <hi>d'Ognate</hi> is, to have the upper Auſtria reſtored; and that for his expences in the warre, the Duke of Bavaria have the Electorall Dignity, and the upper Palatinate, which as the Count of Zol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lern tels me doth ſurmount his charges. And a little after: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I believe, the Count
<pb facs="tcp:8197:26"/>
                  <hi>d'Ognate,</hi> nor his miniſter will ever aſſent to the Tranſlation, unleſſe it be for their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; thereby to draw into their owne clutches, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Palatinate, as a Country, which much importeth the houſe of Auſtria, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Empire and of the Netherlands. For by that meanes, the Dutch Proteſtants can neither aſsiſt the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, nor the Hollanders the Dutch Proteſtants; and ſo the King of Spaine would bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Low Countreyes, and the Emperour in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:26"/>
            <p>It is alſo very remarkeable, what the Duke of Bavaria promiſed, under his hand and ſeale, in the treatie of Vlm, which Hee concluded by interpoſition of the French King, with the Proteſtants then united the <hi>5 of Iuly</hi> 1620. where Hee aſſured them in the word of a Prince, and in the moſt valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble forme in law, \
<q>
                  <p>That none ſhould invade or moleſt the Lands, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, Townes, Borroughs, vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages or poſſeſsions of any of the Electours, temporall or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall; nor ſhould any wayes trouble one another in their government or Religion. But that the Evangeliks, as well as the Catholikes, ſhould live in concord together, leaving one another to enioy their owne in
<pb facs="tcp:8197:27"/>peace. </p>
               </q>
And in the <hi>third Article of the ſaid</hi> Treaty, where the Kingdome of Bohemia and incorporated provinces are excluded; 
<q>
                  <p>The Electorall Palatinate, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the hereditary lands ſcituated in the Empire, are expreſſely comprehended. </p>
               </q>
Which the ſaid Duke of Bavaria did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confirme, by his Letters, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to Our moſt honoured Lord and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but alſo to the States of the upper Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate, even after Hee had accepted the Commiſſion, againſt the Kingdome of Bohemia and Count. Mansfelt, as the words of notification ſent from Strau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing <hi>the</hi> 8 <hi>of September</hi> 1621 doe teſtifie:
<q>
                  <p>That for his perſon he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with the upper Palatinate, nor had ever done it any wrong. </p>
               </q>
All which agreeing with the Emperours promiſe made to my
<pb facs="tcp:8197:27"/>Lord Digby, for a ſuſpenſion of Armes the beginning of <hi>September</hi> 1621. whereby He declared; 
<q>
                  <p>That ſo long as the Treatie of peace ſhould laſt with the King of Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, Hee would grant no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commiſsion to execute the Ban, againſt the upper Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate. </p>
               </q>
Our deare Lord and Father had little reaſon to miſtruſt any violence or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility from the ſaid Duke of Bavaria; who nevertheleſſe contrary to all the declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhortly after, executed a new and ſharpe commiſſion againſt the Countries, people and ſubiects of Our deare Lord and Father; &amp; whilſt a peace was treating both at Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and Bruxels, He uſurped the whole upper Palatinate, &amp; part of the Nether with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Reſidence, pretending, that his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Commiſsion, was inforced by certaine new commandements from the Emperour, which it befitted not him to examine. And
<pb facs="tcp:8197:28"/>in his Letter to my Lord <hi>Digby</hi> from the Campe at Schartzenfield, 2. <hi>October</hi> 1621. Hee ſaith,
<q>
                  <p>That being now in full march, it was not poſsible for Him to retire; neither could He ever be of advice, to yeeld to a ſuſpenſion of Armes which was ſo ſudden and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly required, even when His enemy was before His face, and He might under that colour, take ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt Him.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Emperour alſo writing to the ſaid Lord <hi>Digby</hi> from Vienna, the 12. <hi>October,</hi> 1621. maketh this anſwere. 
<q>That the Duke of Bavaria, being forced to march againſt the Count of <hi>Mansfelt,</hi> could not deſiſt from
<pb facs="tcp:8197:28"/>that neceſſary expedition, nor allow the ſuſpenſion of Armes propounded, both becauſe his Army was levied at ſuch great charges, and for that, Hee had the victory in his hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which contrary proceedings, ſeemed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange, both to my Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> who was forced to ſee the upper Palatinate, loſt under his eyes, and to the King of Great Brittaine his Maſter, as appeareth by their ſeverall complaints. From Newburg the 5 of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1631. Thus my Lord <hi>Digby</hi> writeth to the Emperour:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">Complaints of my Lord <hi>Digby</hi> to the Emperour.</note>Vnder your Maieſties fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, I hold this hoſtile inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Duke of Bavaria in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Palatinate to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all right and reaſon, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch that I have beene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
<pb facs="tcp:8197:29"/>informed, by your Maieſties Councellours, that the ſaid Duke, neither had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from your Maieſty, to goe on with the execution of the Ban, nor ſhould have any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</q>
But moſt conſiderable are thoſe Letters of King <hi>Iames</hi> His Maſter, before alleadged to the Emperour, dated from Royſtone the 12. of <hi>November</hi> 1621. 
<q>Wherefore we cannot enough marvell,<note place="margin">Complaints of King <hi>Iames</hi> to the Emperour.</note> that at the ſame time, whiles we are treating a peace, and propounding ſaving Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, yea, and that quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arary to your owne anſwere, Our Sonne in law, ſhould bee ſpoyled of his inheritance, and the upper Palatinate taken in
<pb facs="tcp:8197:29"/>by the Duke of Bavaria, at your commandement, and that upon new reaſons, till now, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of. Conſidering that in your ſaid anſwer, given to Our Ambaſſadour, the execution of the Ban was ſuſpended, in thoſe parts, and no Armes to be reſumed, without notice gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Vs, three moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. All which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, after the ſaid anſwer, and by your expreſſe order, the greateſt part of the nether Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate, was ſeized on, by the Spaniſh troopes, and all the reſt indangered, if it had not beene timely prevented.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:30"/>
            <p>After all theſe things, were thus ſecretly plotted, and compaſſed, much about the time, that my Lord <hi>Digby</hi> was ſoliciting the reconcilement, and reſtitution of our deare Lord and Father, and was filled with faire hopes, The Emperour called a Diet at Ratiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, where Himſelfe was in preſence toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the three Spirituall Electours, the Landgrave of Darmſtatt, and Biſhop of Saltzburg, and although both his Majeſty, and Electour of Mentz in name of all the reſt did ſeriouſly require the two temporall Electours of Saxonie and Brandenburg to repaire thither in perſon, yet they onely ſent their Ambaſſadours with this excuſe, that ſince they could not approve the execution of the Ban, nor tranſlation of the Electorall Dignity, which was then reſolved, they were afraid to aſsiſt in preſence, leſt they ſhould bee forced to behold thoſe things, againſt which they had voted, as hereafter we ſhall ſee more at large. At that time our Royall Grand-father, the King of Great Britaine, though much offended, that the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:30"/>treatie at Bruxells propounded by the Emperour was broken off under ſhew: 
<q>That affaires of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance could be neither treated, nor decided without the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and intervention of the Electours, and Eſtates; </q>
yet hearing of this Diet commanded my Lord Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter then in the Palatinate to repaire to Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisbone; whither alſo my Lord <hi>Digby</hi> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at that time in the Emperours Court for the affaires of the Palatinate, alſo reſorted, as to prepare the other Ambaſſadours way, But the King Our Grandfather being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the Emperour was fully reſolved actually to inveſt the Duke of Bavaria with the Electorall Dignity, and that the two temporall Electours upon that reaſon, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented themſelves, countermanded the ſaid Lord Chicheſter, ſuppoſing, that his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence there would not onely be fruitleſſe, but alſo lyable to diſhonour, in ſtead whereof
<pb facs="tcp:8197:31"/>Hee wrote to the King of Spaine, 22. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1622. reſenting this breach of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and unjuſt proceedings in theſe words: 
<q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Letters of King James reſenting the double of the Emperour to the King of Spaine.</note>We are certainly advertiſed, that the Emperor hath bound himſelfe, by diverſe promiſes, to transferre upon the Duke of Bavaria the Palatinate, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of Our Sonne in law, as ye ſhall further underſtand by Our Ambaſſadour, and that your Miniſters have declared to the Emperour, that if this be done without your appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, He muſt looke no more for your aſsiſtance, which is ſo neceſſarie for him: Inſomuch that to put the ſame in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nothing reſteth, but your
<pb facs="tcp:8197:31"/>conſent. Of which proceedings ſo contrarie to all aſſurance gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us of the Emperours good intentions, we are now no leſſe aſtoniſhed, than at firſt Wee were in beleeving. For in all his owne anſwers, made to Our Ambaſſadours, hee not onely declared his friendſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, but promiſed the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire reſtitution of Our Son in law, for a token and teſtimonie thereof. And in all conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which Our ſaid Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours have had with his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State, they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely avowed, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour would never have made us ſuch anſwers, had hee
<pb facs="tcp:8197:32"/>not beene fully free and unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged. Now albeit our care be much encreaſed by ſuch a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine change; yet it is in part diminiſhed, by the conſtant and ſincere good will, which yee have alwaies borne us; wherefore wee intreat you to finiſh this worke, which yee have ſo well begun, and not to ſuffer under pretence of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie in Religion; or of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward intereſts; to fill the ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice or ambitions of a few; that occaſion bee given, of greater evill, and calamities, which by warre, will neceſſarily, fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Chriſtendome; The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples being infinite, how
<pb facs="tcp:8197:32"/>dangerous a thing it is, to drive any to utter deſperation.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding that the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of the two Electours, Saxonie and Brandenburg, laboured hard, in the ſaid Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, to hinder the pretended Inveſtiture, and directly opined againſt the proceedings of the haſty proſcription, and rigorous executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame, as alſo againſt the tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Electorall, trailing with it many prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall inconveniences; yet the Emperour ceaſed not to conferre with all ſolemnity the ſaid Inveſtiture; declaring and conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therein, as it appeareth by his finall reſolution, taken upon the laſt adviſe of the ſaid Electours, 23. <hi>Februar.</hi> 1623. 
<q>
                  <p>That as he never purpoſed, in the leaſt manner whatſoever, to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate either from the preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of Electours, or from the Conſtitutions of the Empire,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:33"/>or his owne Capitulations: ſo hee did not intend by this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture to prejudice any in his right; To which end Hee would have this clauſe inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the inveſtiture of the Duke of Bavaria, namely [That it ſhould no wiſe wrong the Emperour, or the Empire, or the children of the Palatine, or his brother, or the Duke of Newburg, or any other of his Agnation, who might juſtly have any pretence; All which ſhould be expreſſely reſerved, and withall poſsible ſpeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided by tranſaction or by law.] Inſomuch that upon ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence given in favour of the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:33"/>Palatines brother and next of Kin, the Electorall Dignitie, and what ſhall be more adjud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſhall eſcheat and belong unto them after the death of <hi>Maximilian</hi> Duke of Bavaria, wherein they ſhall be alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted by the Emperour; And hereunto the ſaid Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia upon communication had thereof, not fruſtrating the good opinion of the Electours, Princes, and Ambaſſadours now aſſembled, hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated himſelfe, and is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to prouide ſufficiently for that point by his Reverſall let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wherein He hath ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtified his true intentions
<pb facs="tcp:8197:34"/>to the Emperour and Empire, and to publike peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame was confirmed by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his letters, to our ſaid Royall Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, the King of Great Britany dated, from Ratisbone the <hi>5. March,</hi> 1623. wherein are theſe words: 
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Letters of the Emperour confirming the ſame to King <hi>Iames.</hi>
                  </note>Concerning your Nephewes by your daughter, and thoſe of the Palatines Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; as it was never in Our thoughts to prejudice the right of any, by this Our decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; ſo it is our will, that a doore of grace and equitie bee alwaies left open to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſucceſsion in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Dignitie.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here we will ſet aſide, what paſſed from
<pb facs="tcp:8197:34"/>the firſt beginning, at Rome, betwixt the Pope and Cardinals, for advancing this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious tranſlation and Inveſtiture; as alſo. What was promiſed by the Duke of Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, to the See of Rome, in acknowledge, ment of his due obligations, all to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of the honour and preeminence of the Empire. But ſoone after that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture was diſpatched, Our Electorate, Princedomes, Countries, people and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, were in a manner ſtrange and unuſuall in the Empire, torne and ſhared into diuerſe peeces. Our Princedome of the High Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate was conveyed hereditarily, to the Duke of Bavaria, for the redemption of the upper Auſtria, which was morgaged to him by the Emperour, for his charges in the warre. Afterwards, the Governments of the Low Palatinate, on the ſame ſide of the Rhine, were ſet unto him at ſale, on a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine price, as appeareth by the Briefes, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to Our Subjects. The moſt part of the Nether Palatinate, on the other ſide, was conſigned into the hands of the King of
<pb facs="tcp:8197:35"/>Spaine by way of compenſation, for the great coſts, which he pretended in the war. The Government of Germerſhein fell to the Arch-Duke Leopald, Vtzberg and Vmſtat to the Landgrave of Darmſtat: The Berg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat to the Biſhop of Mentz, Barchſtein and Weiden to the Duke of Newburg. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there were, who carried away peeces of our Inheritance, as if it had been a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſpoile. All which was flat contrary to the Golden Bull, to the fundamentall lawes of the Empire, to the Rights, Cuſtomes, Priviledges, and Inveſtitures of former Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, and to the promiſes of this. For the Golden Bull doth in many places clearely forbid the renting and diſmembring of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall and feudall Countries. In the 24 <hi>Chapter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lawes againſt diſmembring the lands of Electours.</note> thus it ſtands: 
<q>We therefore will and ordaine as a perpetuall law, that the High and Noble Princedomes, to wit, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Bohemia, the County Palatine of the Rhine, the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:35"/>Dukedome of Sax. &amp; the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſate of Brandenburg toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther withall their lands, limits, homages and Fees thereon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending ſhall in no wiſe bee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered or devided, but ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine whole and entire for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And in the 20 <hi>chapter</hi> thus: We ordaine by this our Imperiall Act to endure for ever, that every one of the ſaid Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, their ſeverall Rights, Voyces, Offices, and Dignities Electorall with their appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ſhall inſeparably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ioyned and united. And a little after: Seeing therefore theſe bee things inſeparable, they can neither be divided in
<pb facs="tcp:8197:36"/>themſelves, nor by iudgment of any Court, neither ſhall any one bee heard, who ſoliciteth ſuch a ſentence: or if perchance any hearing, ſuite, or ſentence; ſhall bee hereafter ſought, or granted, by errours or other meanes, againſt this our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent act, We declare the ſame, and whatſoever ſhall follow thereupon, to be nought in law, without worth and validity.</q>
By all which paſſages, every eye may ſee, where this tranſlation, Inveſtiture, ſharing, dividing, bargaine and ſale of our Eſtates Dignities, are to be lodged. But for all, that the Duke of Bavaria was thus inveſted, and put in Poſſeſſion of the Electorall Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Voyce, and Office; it coſt both Him, and the Emperour himſelfe much paines
<pb facs="tcp:8197:36"/>and labour, and that not without certaine Articles and conditions, before they could induce the two Electours of Saxony and Brandenburg, to receive him into their Seſſion and ſociety in the Colledge. To beginne which worke, the Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia brake the yce, earneſtly requeſting the Electour of Mentz, then living, by letters dated at Ratisbone 4 of March 1623 to doe his beſt offices with the Duke of Saxony, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring reciprocally:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Declaration of the Duke of Bavaria to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctourſhip:</note>That ſince it pleaſed his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſty to thinke it neceſſary for the common good, to conferre the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Dignity, then vacant, upon him, and that in ſuch a forme, as preſerved the Right of Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and intereſt therein, He had ſubmitted to His Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pleaſure, and was ready by
<pb facs="tcp:8197:37"/>the helpe of God to confirme Himſelfe, and all his actions, to what the Golden Bull, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Dignity, the lawes of the Empire, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, the ſanction of Civill and religious peace did require.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Whereupon the Electour of <hi>Ments</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to deale with the Duke of Saxony, and many reaſons to perſwade Him, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Duke of Bavaria for Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour as appeareth by his letters from Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisbone the 11 of <hi>March</hi> 1623. from <hi>Aſchaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenburg</hi> 7 <hi>October</hi> 1623. Item the 3 <hi>Novemb.</hi> &amp; 8 <hi>December</hi> of ſame yeare, as alſo from thence of the 13 <hi>February</hi> 1624. ſent to the Electour of Brandenburg. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Emperour himſelfe preſſed the ſaid Electours by many meſſages, and exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, wherein He uſed the Marquis <hi>Erneſt</hi> of Anſpach, and principally the Baron <hi>Hanniball</hi> of Dohna: yea, and to make the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:37"/>matter the more eaſie, the Electour of <hi>Mentz</hi> tooke a iourney to the Electour of Saxony, in perſon: Inſomuch that after much writing, divers conferences, ſpecious arguments, and faire promiſes, the buſineſſe was ſo farre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, that the Electour of Saxony was at laſt diſpoſed to conſent, yet with certaine limitations. And becauſe the Electour of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> ſtill withſtood, the King of Poland deceaſed, was ſet upon him, who by letters dated at <hi>Warſow</hi> 26 <hi>April</hi> 1625. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted him, not without ſome comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to allow of the ſaid ſociety: And the Duke of Saxony had a meeting with him to the ſame end, for, ſo Hee writeth to the Emperour from Setzenvoda the 4 of <hi>November</hi> 1626.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That having often repeated unto the Marquis of Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg the deſire of his Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maieſty, and his owne; and earneſtly intreated him to tell
<pb facs="tcp:8197:38"/>him freely, whether He would acknowledge the Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia in the forme preſcribed: He found Him ſomewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpoſed, than before; and hoped He had beene won, but Hee well perceived, that Hee would not ſo eaſily declare his reſolution, unleſſe His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty would bee pleaſed to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon him once againe. </q>
Thereupon the Baron <hi>Hannibal</hi> of Dona was ſent to the Electour of Brandenburg in <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1627. to induce him to allow of the ſaid reception, as appeareth by his inſtruction dated at Vienna 26 of <hi>December,</hi> 1626.</p>
            <p>The chiefe reaſons, motives and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whereby the ſaid Electours were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come are contained in the Letters of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> deceaſed the 7 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1623. and eſpecially of the 3 <hi>November of</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:38"/>yeare, to this purpoſe:
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Letters of the Electour of Mentz perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</note> Whereas by experience of all times, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Colledge hath beene held as a foundation whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head, as well as the members, and ſo the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Empire doth reſt, ſo long as there is a rupture in the Colledge, the Generall Eſtates cannot be united, and whiles they are in diviſion, the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Empire can never be appeaſed. It is therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary before all things, to cure &amp; unite the Colledge, and knit the Electours in mutuall concord and affection, for a time at leaſt, if not for ever. To which end my opinion is, that
<pb facs="tcp:8197:39"/>the expedient, which his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Majeſty graciouſly ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at Ratisbone about the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine Electorate, be approved of us all, if not abſolutely, at leaſt with ſuch reſtitutions, whereby both the Electorall houſes of the Empire, and the next of the ſaid Palatines Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation bee fully ſecured from the apprehenſion of any preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. To prevent which, if any were to be feared, I ſhould hope that neither His Imperiall Majeſty, nor if neede were, the Electour of Bavaria, would thinke it unfitting to graunt letters of Recogniſance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by teſtifying, that the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:8197:39"/>Tranſlation ſhall in no wiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate, to the Feodall Rights of Princely or Electorall hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nor to the ordinances of the Golden Bull, nor yet to thoſe, to whom after the outlawry of the Count Palatine, the ſaid E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Dignity doth of Right belong, whoſe claime after the death of the Electour of Bavaria, ſhall remaine whole and inviolable. This would be the onely remedy to ſave all mens pretentions to uphold the Electorall preheminence, to heale the breaches of the Empire, to quench the fire of warre, and prevent the kindling of it by reſtleſſe men.</q>
               <pb facs="tcp:8197:40"/>In another letter of the ſaid Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> to the Electour of <hi>Brand.</hi> the 13 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1624 hee averreth: 
<q>That the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſubſiſtence of the Empire depended wholly upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uniting of the Electorall Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, without which it was impoſsible to quiet the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</q>
And in the Baron of Donas foreſaid Inſtruction, it is alleaged: 
<q>That ſince a publike peace and union in the Empire is altogether hopeleſſe,<note place="margin">The Emperors Inſtruction to the Baron of Dona ſent to the Electour of Brandenburg about the Tranſlation.</note> without it bee firſt redintegrated in the Colledge; ye ſhall therfore in Our name, require the Electour of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg, not to ſeparate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe any longer from the reſt of his fellowes, nor to make a
<pb facs="tcp:8197:40"/>rent in the moſt ſupreame and ſecret Councell of the Roman Emperour, thereby to foment the combuſtions of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which can onely be aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the joynt Councell and concurrence of the Electorall Body. But yee ſhall let Him known, that by acknowledging, and receiving the Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia for a Coelectour in the Colledge, Hee ſhall ſhew his zeale, and affection (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the confidence we have conceived of Him,) not onely to uphold our Imperiall great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but alſo to conſerve the ſacred Empire in the Bond of peace and the rather, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:8197:41"/>by this meanes the amiable times of meetings and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, will againe bee reſtored both in the Colledge of Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and in publike Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Diets, to his immortal praiſe and honour, having contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo much, to the long deſired weale, and tranquillity of the Empire.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the moſt pregnant Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then alleaged, to the ſaid Electours of Saxony and Brandenburg. Since which time, common experience hath manifeſted to the world, whether by tranſlating of the Electorate, or introducing the Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia into the Colledge, the peace ſo much pretended, hath beene ſought, or eſtabliſhed, or els inſtead thereof infinite hatreds, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, miſeries, and bloudy deſolations, have not beene raiſed to the ruine and extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
<pb facs="tcp:8197:41"/>of the Empire. That all men may therefore know, with what zeale and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, the ſaid Electours of Saxony and Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg oppoſed, from the firſt beginning, both the Ban publiſhed without their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or aſſent, and alſo the tranſlation grounded thereupon; as likewiſe with what limits and reſervations they received the Duke of Bavaria into the Electorall Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; We will firſt produce the ſuffrages, of their Ambaſſadours, at the Diet of Ratisbone 1623, uppon the points of Proſcription and Tranſlation, as they were preſented to the Emperour, and recorded in the Chancery of the Electour of <hi>Mentz</hi> 18 <hi>of Feb.</hi> 1623. Thus ranne the ſuffrage of the Saxonians: 
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Suffrage of the Saxons, in the Diet of Ratisbone againſt the Tranſlations.</note>Concerning the proceedings of the Ban, and execution therein decreed, againſt the Count Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine; the Electour of Saxonies Highneſſe leaveth that apart, as a thing done againſt his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:42"/>and without due forme of proceeding. Foraſmuch as the matter being of ſuch impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance touching a member of the Electorall Colledge, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it the deſtruction of the Empire, the votes and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the whole Colledge ſhould firſt have beene requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red according to the forme of Capitulations, in that caſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding; That no Prince or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour ſhould bee outlawed without a legall hearing and juſt forme of proceeding, and who will looke unto the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Magdeburg and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha, no more but Townes, which were proſcribed in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall
<pb facs="tcp:8197:42"/>Diets, held at Augſpurg under the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> V. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> I. <hi>Maximillian</hi> II. in the yeares 1551. 1554. 1566. ſhall finde, that former Emperours were wont to uſe ſuch te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate Circumſpection, that they firſt demanded the Councell not onely of the Electours and Princes, but of the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, before they proclaimed the Ban, or commanded execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Concerning the Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Electorate, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth verily thinke that inſtead of being a meanes to eſtabliſhed a publike peace, for which end, this Dyet was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, it may prove a cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:8197:43"/>of greater diviſion, and a fire-brand of warre, to conſume the Empire. Therefore Hedeemeth the reſtitution of the Palatine (though upon due terms of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion) to be above all things neceſſary to obtaine this ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led peace; for the purchaſing whereof, more regard ſhould be had to the publike, than to any other conſideration. This being certaine, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire can never bee quieted by rigour and extremity, but will rather bee forced to keepe in armes, and expoſed to daily danger. Moreover, this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, although it concerneth a member of the Electorall
<pb facs="tcp:8197:43"/>Colledge, and bee the moſt weighty buſineſſe, can fall out in the Empire; yet it hath beene done, without their knowledge, and even in this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, onely intimated unto them, as a thing concluded, without ever asking their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or approbation: A courſe never taken before this day. For albeit the examples of this kinde, are ſo few, that onely one is found; where the Electour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was tranſlated for delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency; yet wee may therein obſerve another kind of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding. The caſe happened, in the time of <hi>Charles the fift,</hi> and in the perſon of <hi>Frederick Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8197:44"/>of <hi>Saxony,</hi> who renouncing his homage, and obligation to the Emperour, his Electour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was promiſed and aſsigned to <hi>Duke Maurice</hi> in the Camp of Suntham, <hi>the</hi> 27. <hi>October.</hi> 1546. where the formall words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the ſaid promiſe was made by due courſe, counſell and deliberation of the chiefe States of the Empire. The 19. <hi>May</hi> in the Campe at Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg 1547. the ſaid Duke <hi>Fredericke</hi> renounced the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctourſhip, and <hi>the</hi> 21. <hi>May</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a particular Act thereof, with Obligation. <hi>The</hi> 4. <hi>of Iune,</hi> of the ſaid yeere, the Electour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Office of high Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:44"/>with all the appurtenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, was transferred upon Duke <hi>Maurice</hi> in preſence of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, Electours, Princes, and forraine Nations, with power to make uſe of the Right and Title thereunto belonging. <hi>The</hi> 24. <hi>February</hi> 1548. the ſaid Duke <hi>Maurice,</hi> was ſolemnely inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted at Ausburg, under the Skie, and received into the Fellowſhip and Seſsion of the Colledge, by all the Electours, who by a ſpeciall Act, teſtified, that all was done, by their knowledge and approbation: by all which circumſtances, it appeareth, that the promiſe of the Tranſlation, and the Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of the ſaid Electorate, was
<pb facs="tcp:8197:45"/>publikly done, in the preſence, &amp; by allowance of all the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours. Beſides that, it may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeare, how that by this Tranſlation, the publike peace, whereat it aimeth, cannot bee attained. His Highneſſe doth profeſſe, that although the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt extremities ſhould be uſed, yet neither the children of the Count Palatine, nor His Brother, and the reſt of that Agnation, cannot legally bee excluded, in regard of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, from their claime and recover of the ſaid Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Lands, &amp; Dignities; and to ſhew, that they have no mind to be deprived of their Right ſo long acquired to their
<pb facs="tcp:8197:45"/>Houſe, the inſtances of the ſaid Brother, of the Duke of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, and of the other Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, by their Ambaſſadours here preſent, made to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Majeſty, and the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Colledge, do ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifie. For this kind of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture, called in the Empire ſimultaneous, is of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and condition, then the cuſtome of common Fees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purchaſed and received in every mans proper Right, by taking an oath, and touching of a ſword, whereof no man therein comprehended, can be further deprived, then for himſelfe, and for his owne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence:
<pb facs="tcp:8197:46"/>which truth is cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exemplified in the perſon, of the Duke <hi>Mauritius,</hi> a forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: for although the Elector, Duke <hi>Fredericke,</hi> was lawfully depoſed, and His brother Duke <hi>Erneſt,</hi> excluded by the Ban for their owne offences; yet that tainted not the Duke <hi>Mauritius,</hi> who after them was the next of blood, &amp; by that Right, ſucceeded: for it had not beene neceſſary to have deprived Duke <hi>Erneſt</hi> the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Ban, if a third party innocent, could have forfeited his Right by the crime of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: In Summe. <hi>Poenae debent tenere ſuos Authores;</hi> being a thing
<pb facs="tcp:8197:46"/>unjuſt, to take from any man, his inherent Right, who by no fault of his owne had unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe. This Law there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo long rooted, in the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Electors; and temporall Princes, cannot bee diſſolved without infinite prejudice, to them all; who for the crime of any one man, might be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to the uncertainty of their claimes and tenures, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed of their naturall Rights and Succeſsions, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were inculpable; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is a thing unfit to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, and unanſwerable to poſterity.</q>
In another ſuffrage, of the ſaid Saxonian Ambaſſadours, this is added.
<q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8197:47"/>The reaſons alledged by His Highneſſe, the Electour of of Saxe, upon the point of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, are founded upon the groundary Lawes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the wellfare of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire repoſeth, and which are left as certaine, ſtable, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable rules: from whence the Arguments, which are likewiſe drawne, are confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with examples; which plainely ſhew, what great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe the Emperours, <hi>Charles</hi> the V. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the I. and <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imilian</hi> II. deceaſed, uſed in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of a Ban.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Suffrage of the Brande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>burgers againſt the ſame.</note>The Ambaſſadours of the Electour of Brandenburg opined in this manner;</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:47"/>
            <q>
               <p>They could not but repeate their former ſuffrage concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the propoſition, not being yet able to conceive, by what reaſon the Electours can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from a buſineſſe of ſuch moment, that the good or bad Eſtate of the whole Empire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth thereupon. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation ſolemnly made, and ſworne, requireth, that in all important caſes, the Counſells of the Electours ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and expreſſely preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in any buſineſſe, which mought happily fall out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Emperour, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours, or Imperiall Eſtates.
<pb facs="tcp:8197:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8197:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8197:49"/>But although there had beene no ſuch publike Capitulation, yet the affaire of it ſelfe, is of ſuch conſequence, concerning an Electour and his Dignity; that it ought not, to bee ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred from their cogniſance and advice; and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, it chiefly touching the Emperours houſe; the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof to the Electours, would have cut off all occaſion of jealouſie or complaint; that His Majeſty had been too haſty in His owne cauſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſeeing that the forme of a ſuite and ſentence, is a part of juſtice; and that juſtice can bee no wiſe better adminiſtred,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:49"/>than according to the Lawes, enacted and eſtabliſhed, it had been very juſt and neceſſary, not to have condemned, the Count Palatine, before His cauſe had been duely heard, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the cuſtome of the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Chamber. If it be replyed, That the crime of the Palatine, was ſo notorious, as it needed not a formall ſuite; That will hardly hold water: for in the Capitulation (which, without all queſtion, is a fundamentall Law, and of ſtrict obſervance) there is no ſuch diſtinction found; and where it doth not diſtinguiſh, our part is, to be ruled. Albeit, the writings,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:50"/>which are abroad, ſeeme to proove, that this, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led notorious, is a particular caſe, and the proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, doe contradict the Royall Capitulation. Againe, before ſuch a ſentence had been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, many conſiderations ſhould have been had, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances examined, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe, which concerned the children of the Palatine, His Brother, and the next of that Agnation; all of whom, are, as yet, unaccuſed, and therefore much leſſe convinced of any crime: And a little after: The Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation being of no leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then the Ban, did queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:50"/>alike belong to their deliberation; for as they were Electours, and States of the Emperour, ſo were they alſo of the Empire, and were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called, the props and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Empire; and if the Emperour cannot, by His own power, beſtow any Fee, nor any Towne, fallen in reverſion, without the knowledge of the Electours, and Eſtates, how much more is their aſſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, in transferring of ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame a Tenure of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as is an Electorall Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This would be too grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and great a wrong to the temporall Electours, Princes,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:51"/>and Eſtates, to their children and blood; if without hearing of their cauſe, or privity of the Colledge Electorall, they ſhould be diſpoſſeſſed of their Eſtates and Dignities, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their ſimultaneous and undeprivable Succeſsion: Their Lord and Maſter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that the reſt of his Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Fellowes, would never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of ſuch proceedings, nor be a cauſe, that the condition of an Electour, which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes been of ſuch ſway, in the Empire, ſhould become worſe, than a Gentlemans in Poland; who cannot be proſcribed, but in a Diet of the Kingdome.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:51"/>
            <p>In the anſwere, which the Electours and Princes, aſſembled at Ratisbone, together with the Ambaſſadours of ſuch as were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, made unto the Emperours Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, exhibited to them, <hi>the</hi> 30 <hi>of Ianuary</hi> 1623. This was repreſented in the name of the two Electors, of Saxe and Brandenburg. 
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Anſweres made to the Emperour touching the Tranſlation.</note>That, not to ſpeak of the Count Palatines defence, theſe things ought to be duely conſidered, in the point of the Tranſlation. Firſt, whether thoſe of His children, who before His Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawry, were included, by the providence of their Anceſtors, in the Electorall Right and Succeſsion, can afterwards bee excluded. Next, whether His Brother, guiltleſſe of any tranſgreſsion, who neither
<pb facs="tcp:8197:52"/>hath, nor could, by reaſon of his nonage, offend the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour? or whether the kindred, and next of His Agnation, that not onely teſtified their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, but likewiſe their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and fidelity, to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in theſe occaſions, can be juſtly debarred from their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It was further repreſented, in the report of the Electours, and Princes, made upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine points, of the Emperours Propoſition, <hi>the</hi> 15. <hi>February</hi> of the ſaid yeere: 
<q>The Suffrages ſufficiently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, what the opinion was, of the two Electours, of Saxe and Brandenburg, about the point of Tranſlation. And albeit,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:52"/>theſe words <hi>(Without ought pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing.)</hi> were inſerted in the laſt relation, yet their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes have thought good, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract them, foraſmuch as the ſaid words cannot ſtand with the Capitulation, by which His Majeſty is ſo farre, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally bound, that this matter cannot be left to the freedome of His will. For it is expreſly ordained, That no buſineſſe of importance ſhould paſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Electours; and that no Eſtate of the Empire, ſhould be Outlawed, without a due and formall hearing; Which Capitulation, being a
<pb facs="tcp:8197:53"/>fundamentall, and unrepealed law, in the Empire, ought no more to be brought in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but rather obeyed, than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed. And becauſe their Dignities, as Electours tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, deſcended to their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by inheritance; They tooke themſelves, to have the greater intereſt, and ſo the more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to preſerve the ſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, to confirme the votes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, the Electour of Saxe wrote to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> during the ſaid Diet, 23 <hi>February</hi> 1623. to this purpoſe:</p>
            <q>
               <p>VVe hoped, that our good and wholeſome exhortations, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not upon opinions, but upon
<pb facs="tcp:8197:53"/>the lawes and examples of the Empire, would have found more credit than they have done; then, theſe wayes, had not beene taken, which muſt needs leade, to bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and trouble; of which, as we cannot approve, for the Reaſons which ye know; ſo the miſchiefes which may follow thereupon, will juſtifie our innocencie, though increaſe our griefe. Sorry we are, to ſee ſuch proceedings in our dayes, and ſo hopeleſſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy: which maketh us the more conſtant to our former ſuffrages, that are regiſtred in your Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery; deſiring nothing more, than that our ſound and ſincere remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, may hereafter be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:54"/>when the events perhaps, will not anſwere to the deſignes. And a little after: What? if in the proſcribing an Electour, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing another in his roome, the adviſe of Electours be not taken, we ſee not, wherein conſiſteth that Authoritie, nor how it can be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, not what it differeth from any other Eſtate. To alleadge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity, or that the Colledge ſhall incurre no harme, is but a ſleight excuſe. For Capitulations are <hi>ſtricti juris,</hi> and admit no excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or if any, the interpretations thereof belong to the Colledge in Body, without which, all is in vaine whatſoever is at the preſent promiſed. As for the Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:8197:54"/>it ſelfe, wee never thought it a way to peace, but rather to warre, and could not therefore aſſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. In which opinion, Wee are ſtill the more confirmed, for as much, that ſince the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Golden Bull, the like example, hath not been found; and if wee take that of Duke <hi>Maurice</hi> aboveſaid, it declareth quite the contrary. Beſides that clauſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into his Majeſties reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, touching the Children and Agnation of Electours, in very umbragious, and may rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate, than ſtill the cauſe: for there is decided, that a third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon innocent, may be deprived of his ſimultaneous Inveſtiture, and
<pb facs="tcp:8197:55"/>loſe that inherent Right, which is proper to himſelfe, for the crime, which is proper to another. Where, hence will follow, that the Children and Agnation muſt ſettle their Right by arbitrement, and compoſition, and that, which was before cleare and legall, will now become diſputable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine: but becauſe this doth not alone import, the Palatine Houſe, but all the reſt of Electors and Princes, who have obtained the ſame Inveſtiture by propriety, taking an oath, and kiſsing the ſword; VVe muſt be ſo much the more carefull, not to approve of ſuch a fact, which may endamage the whole Empire.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8197:55"/>
               <p>In another letter to the ſaid Arch-biſhop of Mentz, dated from Dreſden the 10. <hi>of October</hi> 1623. the Electour of Saxe giveth this Councell: It was our true and ſincere affection, firſt to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, as Head of the Empire, and then to all the members, which made us deliver thoſe ſuffrages, in open Councell, regiſtred in the Imperiall Chancery; wherby ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently appeareth, what meanes, we judged fitteſt to obtaine a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled peace. But we have learned by ſad experience, that ſince the ſaid Aſſembly, where that Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was moſt hotly taken, which we eſteemed moſt unpeaceable, all things in the Empire have grown worſe and worſe. And ſomewhat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb facs="tcp:8197:56"/>The reſtitution was propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for this regard; becauſe the Ban, the execution and the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which (as yee know) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thereupon, were all reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved without the knowledge or aſſent of the Electours: which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is nevertheleſſe, neceſſary, if ſo be the Capitulation may have any force, or the Electours be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their Dignities: for you may eaſily judge, as a wiſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, and well verſed in publike affaires, That if, in ſuch high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which concerne the whole Empire, the adviſe of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours bee not regarded, their preheminence will quickly fall, and their perſons bee abaſed, and
<pb facs="tcp:8197:56"/>the pillars of the Empire, and moſt inward Councellours of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Emperour will be vaine ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, without effect. And ſo the Eſtates of the Empire, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe imagine, but that all, which paſſed in the Colledge, is done by the Electours conſent, may juſtly lay the blame upon them, which we beſeech you not to draw, but rather to divert. We deſire not, by this our opinion, to ſtirre up tedious and fruitleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, but onely to diſcharge our oath to the Electorall Colledge, and our care to poſterity. For, ſuppoſe that the Reſtitution of the Palatine be laid aſide, and all the reſt of the proceedings good and
<pb facs="tcp:8197:57"/>due; yet finde wee not, how the Kindred and Agnation, can be excluded, or their Right, ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in their blood, made uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, or ſubjected to a Proceſſe at Law. Foraſmuch as that Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by which they ſucceed, is proper, and fixed in their owne perſons; who are no leſſe bound to take a feodall oath, than the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſour of the Fee: which Right, cannot be forfeited by the fault of another, but onely by their owne; otherwiſe, the innocent would be puniſhed with the guilty; and loyall Liege-men, have no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from diſloyall, which would open a doore to much Felony.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8197:57"/>
               <p>In another Letter of the two ſaid Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of Saxe and Brandenburg, which they joyntly wrote unto the Emperour, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the 12 of <hi>March</hi> 1623. the confirmed their former ſuffrage, with theſe reaſons:</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Letters of the two Electours, to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, joyntly confirming the ſaid Suffrage.</note>Since our Votes, and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, proceed not out of paſsion, or ſuppoſe, to draw matters to delay; but are ſurely groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon nature, and equity, upon examples in the Empire, and upon theſe fundamentall Lawes, and Conſtitutions, which are ſo farre, from our power to change, or abrogate, that we are bound by oath, both to your Majeſty, and to the Empire, to maintaine them: We know not how to vary, or depart of jot from that
<pb facs="tcp:8197:58"/>Declaration, which hath been already made unto your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, by our Ambaſſadours. For if we ſhould reſort in perſon unto your Maieſty, that wee might approve, what is paſſed; we ſhould retract our former ſuffrages, and all the grounds before alledged; from whence, what elſe can be inferred, but that either our intentions, were not ſincere, nor well adviſed; or that our Ambaſſadours had no Commiſsion for what they ſaid: Both which, would turne to our reproach, not onely with the Princes living, (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many are of our advice) but alſo with thoſe to come, and
<pb facs="tcp:8197:58"/>all Poſterity. For as wee willingly confeſſe, that an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour, or Prince offending, may, and ought to be puniſhed for his offence; ſo we hope, your Majeſty will not deny, that the caſe of an Electour, or Prince, ſhould not be worſe in their puniſhment, than a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſon; againſt whom, how notorious ſoever the crime may be, the manner is not to proceed, without adjournment and open hearing. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the power of your Majeſty, is not called in queſtion; but the manner of proceeding, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, according to the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes and Orders of
<pb facs="tcp:8197:59"/>the Empire. Your Majeſty, well knoweth, that by the feo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall Lawes, when a difference ariſeth, betweene the Lord and the Vaſſall, the caſe uſeth to be decided by his Peeres, in Court, bearing the ſame name and Armes. How much more then ſhould this be kept, in perſons of greater Rank; That their advice ſhould be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, who are the inward Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers of your Majeſty; and of the ſame Dignity and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with the Delinquent? Your Majeſty is not likewiſe ignorant, what our Opinions are, concerning the Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Electorate; wherein,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:59"/>we have at large, remarked the courſe of former times; and in the ſame perſiſt. Neither can we conceive, how that Clauſe, annexed to your Majeſties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, which ſendeth the Children, and Couſins, of the Palatine, to ſeeke their Right, by Law and Arbitration, can avoyd, delay, or advance the Peace. For, by that meanes, the Right of Agnation, which, out of all doubt, is inſeparable from their blood, will become litigious, and that made liable, to an uncertaine ſuite, whereof they cannot, in their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, bee deprived, without their owne miſdemeanour: if
<pb facs="tcp:8197:60"/>therefore, we ſhould perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſsiſt, in that deliberation; how, when, or in what maner, the claimes of the ſaid Agnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might be friendly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; or for default of ſuch agreement, might be decided at Law; we ſhould not onely approve, all that is paſſed, but draw upon all Electours, and Princes, who have the like Inveſtiture, an irrecoverable wrong, for which, we could never anſwere, to the ſaid Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; neither can we conceive, how a judicious Court can be erected, to decide this point; ſince all the Electorall, and moſt Illuſtrious Houſes, have
<pb facs="tcp:8197:60"/>intereſt therein. All theſe things therefore conſidered; That wee could neither aſsiſt in preſence, nor depart from the Suffrages of our Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, without prejudice to the Empire, and reproach to our ſelves, we humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your Majeſty, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of our excuſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that if wee ſtood not bound by oath, and the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Lawes, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Empire, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould hinder vs, from giving your Maieſty, free and faithfull obedience.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Now it remaineth to ſet downe, with what forme, limits, and reſervations the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:61"/>two Electours of Saxe and Brandenburg, did at laſt acknowledge, and receive the Duke of Bavaria. The Electour of Saxe writing to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> from <hi>Dreſden,</hi> the 1. <hi>of March,</hi> 1634. declareth himſelfe in theſe tearmes:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Conditions under which the Electour of Saxe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Tranſlation.</note>Wee agree with you; that nothing is more neceſſarie, than the reunion of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Colledge, whereby Diets and Aſſemblies may be called, to conferre in Bodie, of all things expedient for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like peace; at this wee aimed, and this we preſſed, in the late Diet of Electours and Princes at Ratisbone: our difference onely was about the perſons: for yee and the Eccleſiaſticall Electours approved the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:61"/>which we and the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of Brandenburg partly, to preſerve the Authoritie of the Colledge, and partly the quiet and obedience of the Empire, utterly diſſwaded. And although wee propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothing, but what our oath, the Dignitie of our rank, and common tranquillitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; and that all our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were ſo well grounded upon the lawes, ordinances and examples of the Empire, that wee neede not varie, from our firſt mind and intentions: yet becauſe ye and the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Electours are of another opinion; That ye thinke the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:62"/>filling up of the Colledge to be the onely meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure peace, and relieve the Empire, and that yee hope all wrongs and Innovations, may be prevented for the time to come, by Reverſals or other meanes; Wee for our parts, ſhould bee unwilling, to give any occaſion, that the Empire ſhould longer groane, under thoſe miſeries &amp; oppreſsions, which threaten utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And therefore, if the Rights of all Parties, may be ſo provided for, that none may ſuffer wrong, we are contented to redintegrate the Colledge, by acknowledging the Duke
<pb facs="tcp:8197:62"/>of Bavaria for Electour. But before he be put in poſſeſsion, we think it needfull, firſt of all, that all the Armies ſpeedily diſlodge, out of the Lands and Territories of the Electours, Princes, and Townes Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; whereby it may appeare, that the ſaid Duke be received, for reſpect to the Emperour, and zeale of publike peace, rather than by conſtraint: which caution, is the more reaſonable, becauſe the troops of the Duke of Brunſwick, and Count <hi>Mansfelt,</hi> are utterly routed and disbanded, and all the Evangeliks have licenſed their ſouldiers; ſo as there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:8197:63"/>nothing more to be feared, it would be unjuſt and againſt the lawes of the Empire, to burden it with ſouldiers, when there is no warre, and oppreſſe thoſe parts with ſuperfluous charges, which live in quiet and obedience. Secondly, that letters of recogniſance, be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by his Imperiall Majeſty, as alſo by the Duke of Bavaria; fully teſtifying, that neither the Ban of the Count Palatine, nor Tranſlation of the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſhall be any way hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alledged, to the preiudice of the Electorall greatneſſe, and dignity: or of the Golden Bull; or Imperiall Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb facs="tcp:8197:63"/>or elſe of the Electorall Princely Houſes, in their ſeverall Rights, and Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Thirdly, that the Rights of all thoſe, ſhall be no wiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, to whom the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctourſhip Palatine belonged, before the ſaid Ban, or Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but that, in their ſeverall degrees, they may after the death, of the ſaid Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia, be admitted, into their Rights, without delay: Vpon theſe Conditions, we ſhall not refuſe to acknowledge the ſaid Duke, for the preſent; and the rather, becauſe, whatſoever ſhall hereafter happen; the Suffrages, which we have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:64"/>in open Counſell, and which are inſerted in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the Empire, will beare us witneſſe, to all Poſterity; that we failed not, in due time, place, and manner, to repreſent all things, which our oath, and Electorall Office required.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Electour of Brandenburg, in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere given the Baron <hi>Hannibal</hi> of <hi>Dona,</hi> dated at <hi>Coningsberg</hi> 22 <hi>May</hi> 1627. thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth;</p>
            <q>
               <p>The only cauſe, which hath hitherto ſtopped His Highnes, from agreeing to the point of Tranſlation, was, That he thought, it would rather ſowe, the ſeeds of diſcord, than be a bond of peace; and ſtirre up for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
<pb facs="tcp:8197:64"/>Armes, then quiet all at home; ſince, He hath found by experience, to the great loſſe and ruine of His Countrey, as well as other Eſtates; that he was not miſtaken in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. But, foraſmuch as His Highneſſe underſtandeth, that His Imperiall Maieſty is out of hope, that the Empire would ever be appeaſed, unleſſe the Electorall Colledge be firſt unanimouſly conjoyned, by the introduction of the Duke of Bavaria: That, on his part, he might further the Counſells of Peace, and Proſperity of the Empire; and avoyd the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of future Calamities;
<pb facs="tcp:8197:65"/>His Highneſſe is not unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to beare reſpect, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to His Imperiall Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and conforme himſelfe unto His will, by receiving, and acknowledging, the Duke of Bavaria, for a Coelectour, during his life, upon theſe tearmes and reſervations. Firſt, That he intendeth not, by this Act, any way to depart, from the Suffrage and declaration of his Conſcience, made in the Diet at Ratisbone, touching the publication of the Ban, and Tranſlation of the Electorate, thereupon enſuing. Secondly, That thereby, He will nothing derogate, from the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence
<pb facs="tcp:8197:65"/>of the Electorall Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; nor from the Sanctions of the Golden Bull, nor Lawes and Conſtitutions of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; nor the Capitulation Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall; nor yet from the Rights, and Inveſtitures, of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Electorall, and Princely Houſes; againſt any whereof, He meaneth not, that this His Act, ſhall be drawne in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Thirdly, He purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not, in the leaſt manner, to prejudice, by this His declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Cauſe of the Prince Palatine, nor His Children, Brother, Blood, or Agnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; much leſſe to contribute to their excluſion, or any was
<pb facs="tcp:8197:66"/>to charge Himſelfe, with the Palatine Cauſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Wee are not ignorant, that neere, twenty yeeres agoe, and now afreſh, ſince the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of our Electorate, certaine rumours have been ſpread abroad, eſpecially, in the Courts of forraine Princes; as if the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Dignity, had of old, beene an exed to the Houſe of Bavaria, and not of the Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and that heretofore, Contracts of alternation, had beene made and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, betweene both Houſes, that they ſhould enjoy the Dignity, by turnes: All which, hath beene forged to this end; that it ſhould not ſeeme ſtrange, that the Seſsion, and vote Electorall, which had been ſo long neglected, by the Predeceſſours of the Duke of Bavaria, ſhould be reſtored by his indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and returne to the proper houſe: Not to enter into the debatement or this Cauſe, which is a digreſſion from the purpoſe; nor to repeate that, which perſons of quality
<pb facs="tcp:8197:66"/>have publiſhed, to refute this vaine preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; we will wholly referre our ſelves to the Golden Bull, as to that ſupreame and fundamentall law, which can onely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this cauſe; whereby it will appeare, whether the Electorate, belong to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian or Palatine Line; and what is to bee judged of the pretended part of alternation, In the 7. Title, thus we finde it:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">Law for entai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctourſhip, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and not on Bavaria.</note>Since therefore, it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly knowne, to almoſt the whole world, that the King of Bohemia, Count Palatine of the Rhine, Duke of Saxe, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of Brandenburg; have by reaſon of their <hi>Kingdome, and Principalities,</hi> the Right, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage, and Seſsion, to chuſe, with the Eccleſiaſticall Electours, a King of the Romanes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall
<pb facs="tcp:8197:67"/>him Emperour: And that they are therefore eſtabliſhed, as true Electours of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, with authority to make Elections, &amp;c.</q>
And in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the 20. Title; 
<q>Whereas, all and every one of the ſaid Princedomes (by vertue whereof the Temporall Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours have full power, right and ſuffrage, to elect the King of the Romanes, and make him Emperour) together with their rights, functions, dignities, and appurtenances are ſo ſtraightly knit and united, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By another Edict of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the 4. who enacted the Golden Bull,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:67"/>the ſame was confirmed <hi>Anno</hi> 1356 in theſe words: 
<q>That the right of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was annexed and founded upon the County Palatine; his Imperiall Majeſty, and all the other Princes, had certaine knowledge, and no doubt was to be made thereof. </q>
And a little lower: 
<q>For as much as we firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, that the voice and Power Elective are founded with ſuch right <hi>in the lands of the County Palatine,</hi> and office of high Truckceſſe, that the one cannot ſubſiſt without the other. </q>
To this may be added, That the Count Palatine, by reaſon of the Palatinate, and not of the Dutchy of Bavaria is, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally, the <hi>Vicar of the Empire,</hi> as the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:8197:68"/>Bull clearely ordaineth in the 5 title. 
<q>As often as the Empire ſhall fall in vacancy, the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Count Palatine of the Rhine <hi>(by vertue of the Electorate and Princedome Palatine)</hi> ſhall adminiſter the affaires thereof in place of King of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, over all the Countries of the Rhine, Suevia and Franconia.</q>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, that <hi>Ludo vicus,</hi> the Bavarian Emperour, having baniſhed and diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his elder brother, <hi>Rodolph,</hi> Electour Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine, becauſe He had given his voyce and aſſiſtance to <hi>Frederick</hi> the faire, Arch-Duke of Auſtria, againſt himſelfe, he laboured to impoſe upon the children of the ſaid <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph,</hi> reſtored after his death, ſuch a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of alternation: but as it was attempted without right or reaſon, ſo it never had ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:
<pb facs="tcp:8197:68"/>for the Bavarian Line cannot produce one ſole example, that ever executed ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive power; and all their pretentions were fully rejected, and nullified by the Golden Bull; whereas in the Palatine Houſe, the ſaid Right and Dignitie, hath remained, without any interruption, having for the ſpace of three hundred and odde yeeres, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted as Electours and high Truckceſſe at the Elections and Coronations of thirteene Romane Emperours one after another.</p>
            <p>And here the occaſion offereth it ſelfe, to remember without boaſting, the merits of our Predeceſſours and Palatine Houſe, not onely in the Empire, and all Chriſtendome; but eſpecially towards the Houſe of Auſtria; which hath beene oftner exalted to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall power, and great neſſe by our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours than any other, though many times, to their owne diſadvantage. The example of <hi>Rupert Count Palatine King of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> ſhoweth with what zeale and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, He governed the Empire, and pacified the trouble thereof: <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Frederick II.
<pb facs="tcp:8197:69"/>Anno</hi> 1530. valiantly defended the City of Vienna againſt the Turkes, neither ſparing their Eſtates, nor their lifes. Particularly, the ſaid <hi>Frederick</hi> did diverſe great and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervices to <hi>Charles</hi> V. and his brother <hi>Ludovicus</hi> was the chiefe cauſe, that <hi>anno</hi> 1531. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt was elected Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour at Colen, notwithſtanding, that <hi>Iohn</hi> Electour of Saxe, proteſted againſt it for his ſonne. <hi>Rodolph</hi> of Haburg might next to God, thanke <hi>Lodowick, Electour Palatine,</hi> by whoſe meanes Hee was made Emperour, who was the firſt that beganne to advance his houſe, and tranſmit the Dutchy of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria to his poſteritie. The ſame <hi>Lodowicke</hi> ſtood alone, againſt <hi>Adolph</hi> Count of Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw, who by all the reſt was choſen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and mightily laboured, to bring in <hi>Albert</hi> of Auſtria, ſonne of <hi>Rodolph. Rodolph Electour Palatine</hi> chuſe <hi>Fredericke,</hi> Duke of Auſtria, Emperour, againſt <hi>Lodowick</hi> of Bavaria, his owne brother, which coſt Him as is ſaid, his Dignities and Eſtate. And it is well knowne, that the late Emperours
<pb facs="tcp:8197:69"/>
               <hi>Maximilian</hi> the I. <hi>Charles</hi> V. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> I. <hi>Maximilian</hi> II. <hi>Rodolph</hi> II. and <hi>Matthias</hi> have received no ſmall aſſiſtance, and good offices, from the <hi>Electours Palatines our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours,</hi> to attaine the Crowne. Here alſo may not bee forgotten, how true and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, <hi>Our moſt honoured Lord and Father,</hi> dealt with the preſent Duke of Bavaria: not onely viſiting Him in perſon at <hi>Munchen, Anno</hi> 1618 uſing all free communication with Him, but alſo, not long before His journey into Bohemia, recommending to his truſt his Countries and Eſtates, as to one in whom hee had moſt confidence; who alſo at that time, promiſed all kind of good neighbourhood, and to doe no diſpleaſure, as appeareth by their mutuall letters. But eſpecially, <hi>when Our ſaid Lord and Father,</hi> to make him feele his intire affection, gave him his Electorall voyce to be King of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, <hi>Anno</hi> 1619. in theſe words: 
<q>Having ever in Our heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ſee Right and Iuſtice
<pb facs="tcp:8197:70"/>duely adminiſtred in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, all diſorders and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions removed, and the cauſes of forraigne warre prevented, We have among all the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, Electours, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, fixed our thoughts upon the Duke of Bavaria, as upon a Prince, wiſe, peacefull, full of experience, governing His owne Eſtates in quiet, and not engaged in any warre; which We propound, not out of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection to any of the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, much leſſe to the Houſe of Auſtria, which hath often felt and found the good offices of our Electorall Houſe; but only as we conceive the courſe
<pb facs="tcp:8197:70"/>of the preſent affaires, and that according to Our oath, And therefore, in the Name of God, We give Our voyce, to the ſaid Duke of Bavaria.</q>
            </p>
            <p>All which, being in it ſelfe, cleere as the day; we cannot, but thinke it very ſtrange, that, without taking notice, of the aforeſaid demonſtrations, the proceedings againſt our deare Lord and Father, our Selfe, Brethren, Blood, and Agnation, have beene carried with ſuch rigour, and animoſity; taking from Vs, without all forme of juſtice, what God, Our birth and Right hath given Vs. But that, which grieveth Vs moſt of all, is, That not contented, with thoſe exorbitant, and dangerous innovations, the pretended Tranſlation, of Our Electorall Voyce, Place, and Function, with all that thereon depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; hath againe beene ratified, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon the deſcendents of the Duke of Bavaria, and his brothers, and upon the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:71"/>whole <hi>Line of Duke William their father, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed.</hi> Notwithſtanding, that it was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſaid Duke, for the terme of his life, as the Electours of Saxe and Brandenburg were aſſured, who gave their aſſent for no longer time. By which violent, and perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory proceedings, that, which at firſt, was but oppreſſion; and might have vaniſhed with time, will now put on the face of Law, and be made perpetuall. Whereby, We, Our brethren, blood, and Agnation, may be, for ever, deprived, in Our ſpotleſſe innocence, of all the ancient, and inherent Rights of Succeſſion, Reverſion, and ſimultancous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture, inſeparable from Our Houſe; And that without all bounds of Iuſtice, or forme of Law; unaccuſed, unheard without the knowledge, and aſſent of the Electoral Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and to the infinite prejudice of all Electorall, and Princely Houſes, who may reade their owne ſtory in Our Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Indeed, our moſt honoured Lord and Father, was in His life time advertiſed; that the perpetuation of Our Electorate, in the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:71"/>
               <hi>Line of Duke William,</hi> had beene long agoe projected, and more ſpecially, in the late E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Diet at Ratisbone. Wee have alſo heard; That, hereditarily, an Inveſtiture was promiſed, under Seale, to the Duke of Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria; and that to diſpoſe, the Electours, of Saxe and Brandenburg, the more eaſily to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; the peaceable enioying of the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall goods, would be granted to them, for fourty yeeres. But theſe things, being ſo directly contrary, to the former aſſurances; to the declarations of His Imperiall Maieſty; to the proteſtations of the two temporall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours; to the reverſalls of the Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia; to the Golden Bull; to the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes, and to all Right and equity; Wee did forbeare, along time, to give any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to them: Till in the laſt Treaty of Prague, betweene the Emperour, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour of Saxe; We finde, the Tranſlation of Our Electorall Dignity, with all the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances, to bee ſetled, and entailed, upon the <hi>Line of Duke William; for ever;</hi> and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and approved, by the two ſaid Parties
<pb facs="tcp:8197:72"/>Treating, as an Article of Peace, and a Caſe cleerely decided.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Caſe in Law, that the Electourſhip can neither be forfeited, nor tranſlated, but onely by fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in blood.</note>But, for the better underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Point; wee muſt know, That the Electorall, and Soveraigne Eſtates, which hold in Fee, upon the Empire, are farre more tranſcendent, than common Tenures of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. It is true indeed, that Lands and Lordſhips, which deſcend by inheritance, from the laſt Poſſeſſour, to the next heire, are ſubject, to many changes; They may be ſold, morgaged, alienated, attainted, confiſcated, according to the ſeverall Reaſons and Statutes of Law; and all to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice
<pb facs="tcp:8197:72"/>of the lawfull heires: But Electorall Tenures (ſo long as the State of the Empire ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) are warranted, againſt all theſe kind of changes; and but in one onely Caſe, are immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and unreverſable to the Empire, and <hi>that is for deficiency of male Iſſue, by the Fathers ſide, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction of blood;</hi> For when the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Empire, found it at the firſt needfull, for the policy and peace thereof, to erect the Electorall Colledge, and inveſt the three Houſes, of the Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, Saxe and Brandenburg, (which at that time were Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) with the power ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, <hi>there paſſed a Contract be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb facs="tcp:8197:73"/>the ſaid Houſes, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire;</hi> that the ſaid Electorall Dignity ſhould remaine rooted in them, and deſcend, from Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Sonne, and ſo to the next males of the Fathers blood; comprehending all, that ſhould hereafter be borne, as if they had beene then extant: and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling them to ſucceed, in their owne proper, inherent, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alienable Right, for ever. This ſtipulation, in the firſt Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, hath beene a leading Rule, and Preſident, for all after times; wherein, it hath beene, the conſtant uſe, and practiſe, in the Empire, to keepe up the ſame forme; and in all Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:8197:73"/>vacancyes, to admit, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt the next of the male blood, without rub or interruption. This Cuſtome, hath received ſtrength and authority, in the Empire, for the continuance of times, from the foundation of Lawes; from Covenants, and Capitulations; from tryall and experience; from the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of all Eſtates; and from the reverent eſteeme, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violation of it ſelfe, till theſe preſent times. And for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declaration, of this ancient Right, and Regality of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in Electorall Houſes; it hath beene a maxime, and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, delivered in all Ages;
<pb facs="tcp:8197:74"/>that they ſucceed, not by right of inheritance, nor by any will, or diſpoſition, of the laſt poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, but by the providence of their Anceſtours, and by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracters, whereby the Right of every male, who ſhould apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to that Stock and Linage, to the worlds end; was actually included; not onely as preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in their owne time, but as <hi>Compoſseſſours from, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> From which infallible grounds, theſe conſequences naturally will ariſe. Firſt, that it is not in the power of any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or poſſeſſour of theſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Lands, and Dignities,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:74"/>to alienate, or engage them, to the prejudice of their Blood, though it were to pay a Dowry, or redeeme a Captive, or for any other extreame neceſsity; the reaſon is, becauſe they have no further right in them, then during the life of their owne perſons, and cannot therefore alienate the right of others, who by their deceaſe, ſtep into their place, by ſurrogation, and not inheritance. Secondly, no Predeceſſour, nor Father, can by any Felonious crime whatſoever, though it were of the higheſt treaſon, attaint the blood, or forfeit the Right of his Succeſſours, who are not
<pb facs="tcp:8197:75"/>guilty of the ſame crime, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their claime is not from their Father, but from their Stocke, inveſted in their birth and blood, and by Law irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable. Thirdly, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour being onely upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Conditions, by choyce, not by nature, Adminiſtrator of the Empire; on which, theſe Electorall Dignities, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates doe hold, hath no direct power, or dominion, over theſe Tenures, all He can doe, by the uttermoſt of Law, is to lay His Action againſt the right of the party offending; but not againſt the Right of the reſt, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideth in their innocent blood,
<pb facs="tcp:8197:75"/>and is locked up within the barres of immutability, as too noble and precious a gift to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the fact or keeping or inheritance of any poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Since therefore as well the Electorall claime, belonging by Covenant to our Houſe, as the naturall and lawfull poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Eſtates, and Regalities are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by our Anceſtours, and devolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, as the firſt in blood, no earth by pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er whatſoever, can call them into queſtion, or deprive us, our brethren, or Agnation of our right, and much leſſe transferre it to any other, without rearing it out of the faith full cuſtodie of ancient Covenants, ſtable lawes, and venerable cuſtomes, and obtruding forraigne plots and innovations, and making an irreparable rent in the frame and bodie of the ſacred Empire.</p>
            <p>Had wee, our brethren or blood beene
<pb facs="tcp:8197:76"/>as guiltie of crime, as we are laded with pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, yet if any reſpect had beene ſhowne to the ordinances of the Empire, to the Capitulations of Emperours, or to the grave and ſolid remonstrances of the two foreſaid Electours, wee ſhould at leaſt have beene tryed by the law; but ſince the proceedings againſt us, in our tender inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, hath been no leſſe extreme and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, than if we were the moſt obſtinate enemies of the Empire, and higheſt delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents againſt His Imperiall Majeſtie, wee doubt not, but God, in whom we truſt, and who is Iudge of all, will doe us right, and when he pleaſeth, pronounce his ſentence, according to the juſtice and equitle of our cauſe: In the meane time, we hope, that all Kings, Potentates, Electours, Princes, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Perſons whatſoever, that free from partialitie, and voide of paſſion, ſhall examine theſe violent and precipitious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, by our blamelesse innocence, will not only be touched, with a ſenſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of our caſe, but will eſteemethem
<pb facs="tcp:8197:76"/>all as vicious, and unjuſt, and of no force to prejudice our Rights, unto which God and nature, the conſent and ſanction of the whole Empire hath entitle us. And that the rather, both becauſe nothing to this day hath beene, nor can be laid, to the charge of us, or our brethren, as criminall, againſt the Eſtates and lawes of the Empire, or his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſtie, as for that, the ſeyſure of our prerogatives, the detention of our Eſtates, the tranſlation of our Dignity, and the preſent perpetuation of all, like ſo many linkes of uſurpation, <hi>were contrived and compaſſed in the time of our nonage,</hi> whereby wee could not ſooner proteſt, nor oppoſe, nor vindicate our Rights, nor cuter into the government of our affaires, till <hi>now that we have attained our Majority.</hi> Heere wee may note, that if the two Electours, of Saxe and Brand enburg, judged at the firſt, that the tranſlation of our Electourſhip, though but for a time, and reſtrained onely to the perſon, and life of the Duke of Bayaria, would not withſtanding be injurious to the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:77"/>preheminence of the Colledgre Electorall, and to all temporall Princes, as depriving innocents of their inherent, and ſimultane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Right, inveſted in their blood, and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their Stocke againſt all the lawes, Rights, formes, and cuſtomes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and would therefore in ſtead of peace, be a cauſe (as the events have ſhewne) of further exaſperations, and of cruell warres, which might waſte the Empire. How then can they but reſent this preſent Act, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, without ſuit and try all, Wee were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>in Our minority, when wee were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indited, nor could bee guilty of any crime,</hi> and Our Eſtates and Royalties tranſlated from Vs, our brethren and Agnation, to the Line of <hi>Duke William, farre removed, and that for ever.</hi> And what elſe can they judge of it, but as of an attempt and conſpiration ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of, not onely to fill the Empire with miſtruſts, factions, hatreds, and utter deſperations, but likewiſe to outrage the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke of the State, and undermine the very foundations, that upon the rubbage and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb facs="tcp:8197:77"/>of the ſame, might bee raiſed a new and abſolute Domination.</p>
            <p>As long therefore as the Electorall Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſhall be reputed the foundation of the Empire, and the Golden Bull, the Imperiall Capitulation, and the Conſtitutions of State, for inviolable lawes, whereby the whole body ſhould be governed, and knit together, ſo long can neither Wee, Our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, nor Agnation (altogether innocent and inculpable) be deprived of Our Eſtares and Dignities without manifeſt rupture of all Right, and open violation of' humane peace and ſocietie. Neither is it ſufficient to alleadge, the ſucceſſe of armes, and victories gotten in the field, for a proofe and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the juſtice of their cauſe, for then the condition of Chriſtians, and truth of the Religion we profeſſe, would be much worſe than Turkes and Mahumetans: And if any thinke, that their deſignes bee ſo ſmoothly carried, and their ſtrength ſo great, that they may diſſolve, change, and diſpoſe of all things, as they lift, without the feare of any
<pb facs="tcp:8197:78"/>forraigne oppoſition, let them know, that there is no Councell againſt God, nor might againſt his providence, which hath boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the thoughts of men, and ſet a period upon their power; and albeit they may ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount humane vengeance, and outward force, yet great oppreſſions never want an inward worme, to gnaw downe the pillars of pride, and lay them in the duſt, even as it ſhall pleaſe him, who raiſeth and diſpoſeth Princes and tranſporteth Kingdomes for unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Let every one therefore in his owne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall judgment conſider from the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Acts and authenticall letters of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty, from the ſuffrages and other documents of the Electours and Princes temporall, from the infinite and untolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wrongs, diſgraces, and oppreſſions of our Houſe, whether we have not juſt cauſe to publiſh our Complaints againſt theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt proceedings, and to proteſt againſt them before God and the world. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee doe by this preſent and publike
<pb facs="tcp:8197:78"/>Manifeſt in the beſt and moſt ſolemne forme, according to all Right and cuſtome <hi>withstand and protest against them, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them, leaving this our Protestation,</hi> as a perpetuall witneſſe of the outward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done againſt our Right to this Age, and all poſterity.</p>
            <p>And as wee are thus forced to proteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our wrongs, ſo we doe freely profeſſe in the ſight of God, and upon our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that whatſoever hath been recited, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, urged, or proved in this <hi>Manifest,</hi> is onely for the defence and evidence of our juſt cauſe, and for the maintenance of our proper and inherent Rights, devolved to us from our Anceſtours, and not any way to blacke, or deſpite, or offend any living ſoule of what condition ſoever.</p>
            <p>Theſe Aſſeverations being done, wee make our recourſe unto Your Imperiall Majeſty, to all Kings, Electours, Princes and Eſtates, as to the Diſpencers of Iuſtice, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectours of Innocence, and Guardians of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Orphans here below. We appeale
<pb facs="tcp:8197:79"/>
               <hi>â Caeſare male informato, praeoccupato &amp; irato, ad Caeſarem, Electores &amp; ordines Imperii, tan quam Pares Curiae, melius informandos, &amp; affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus vaeuos,</hi> and humbly beſeech your Imperiall Majeſty, That if Our innocence will not move you, yee would bee moved with your ſelfe, and call to mind, your owne finall reſolution, which ye gave to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours and Princes, at the Diet at Ratisbone, <hi>the</hi> 23 <hi>February</hi> 1623. Wherein, yee were pleaſed, to promiſe, and declare; 
<q>That ye never intended, neither was it your will, by any Act, which was paſſed in the Palatine Cauſe, to croſſe, or prejudice the preeminence of Electours; nor your owne Capitulation; nor the Golden Bull; nor Conſtitutions of the Empire; nor, for that buſineſſe, to take, or intrench, from any, the
<pb facs="tcp:8197:79"/>Right, and due, which to any belonged.</q>
By vertue of this, your Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Declaration, confirmed ſince, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Princes, within and without the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; as alſo, for thoſe many inſtances, and mediations, made in Our behalfe, We again beſeech your Majeſty, to reſtore Vs to Our Rights; to Inveſt Vs in Our Electorſhip, and Eſtates; and to protect Vs in the ſame, as a moſt faithfull, and eminent member of the Empire; not ſuffering any hands, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Our Right, nor trouble Vs, in the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poſſeſſion of that, which God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath appointed Vs: Whereby, yee ſhall imitate, the beſt examples of your Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours; who, upon better informations and advice, have left the wayes of rigour, for the wayes of peace: And ſo, ye ſhall uſe that high power, committed to your truſt, to ſtill the preſent ſtormes, to repaire the breaches, heale the fractions, and wounds of your owne members; and to eſtabliſh the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, in peace and unity, which is now falling to deſolation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:80"/>
            <p>And that our owne requeſts may bee the better ſeconded, wee intreat all Kings, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, Princes, and Eſtates, that they would employ their Power, and ſend their exhortations, as in all places, where they ſhal thinke it availeable, ſo eſpecially with His Imperiall Majeſtie, and the Duke of Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, to the end, that being put into the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able poſſeſſion of our proper Rights, and Electorall and Ancient Houſe, which hath produced Kings and Emperours, and done ſuch ſervices both to the Auſtrian and Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Houſe, and ſtood ſo long a prop and pillar of the Empire, bee not razed nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed in our dayes, nor Wee and Our blood, which ſpring up within the walls thereof, to be driven to deſperation, nor ſeek Councels from Neceſſity. Wherein, as they have all ſome intereſt, either in regard of that reproch, which our injuries and affronts unredreſſed, may caſt upon them, with moſt of whom, we have the honour to be allyed, or elſe for the conſequence, which may fall upon themſelves, if this fire bee not
<pb facs="tcp:8197:80"/>timely quenched: ſo they ſhall labour in a moſt Chriſtian work, pleaſing to God, and glorious among men. Which we deſire of them, with this further aſſurance, that our carriage and intentions to His Imperiall Majeſty, &amp; the whole Empire, ſhall be ever ſincere, loyall, and reſpectfull, Zealous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move jealouſies and diſtruſts, to confirme friendſhip, and intelligence to preſerve the rights and authorities of all, and with our power to eſtabliſh publike peace, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the good of all Chriſtendome. And for themſelves, They ſhall lay an eternall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation upon Vs, our brethren, and our whole Houſe, upon all occaſions, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this their favour, and by the faithfull offices of our friendſhip and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to make them thankfull retribution.</p>
            <p>And for concluſion, to cloſe up all, Wee doe heereby ſummon and exhort, all our Liegemen, Vaſſals and Subjects, that hold in fee on our Electorall Houſe, in due time, not to faile of doing homage, faith, loyalty and obedience unto us, as to their naturall Lord
<pb facs="tcp:8197:81"/>and Prince, hoping that every one of them, will bee carefull to diſcharge their bonds and duties, and take heed of failing, under the Cenſure of the lawes, by any felonious or diſobedient act.</p>
            <p>Heere ſhall end our preſent <hi>Manifest,</hi> which for defence of Our inſeparable rights, and information of the whole world we were faine to publiſh, by inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at London <date>the <hi>12.</hi> of Ianuary, <hi>1636.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Charles Lodowicke,</hi> Electour.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:81"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:8197:82"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
